<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>This is retrospective facilitation</title>
    <description>A Podcast interviewing thought leaders and experienced retrospectives facilitators.
</description>
    <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 24 Nov 2020 16:26:16 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Nov 2020 16:26:16 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reflection on Cynefin helping Agile Retrospectives</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/935165053&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&amp;amp;visual=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;font-size: 10px; color: #cccccc;line-break: anywhere;word-break: normal;overflow: hidden;white-space: nowrap;text-overflow: ellipsis; font-family: Interstate,Lucida Grande,Lucida Sans Unicode,Lucida Sans,Garuda,Verdana,Tahoma,sans-serif;font-weight: 100;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/tirfpodcast&quot; title=&quot;This is retrospective facilitation&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;&quot;&gt;This is retrospective facilitation&lt;/a&gt; · &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/tirfpodcast/reflection-cynefin-helps-agile-retrospectives&quot; title=&quot;Reflection - Cynefin helps Agile Retrospectives&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;&quot;&gt;Reflection - Cynefin helps Agile Retrospectives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is going to be a shorter episode on Cynefin and how it can help agile retrospectives. Cynefin is Cognitive Edge’s sense making framework. It helps, in my opinion, to determine what kind of issues we’re tackling in our retrospectives. Is it something simple that has a straight forward solution? Or do we need to reflect a little bit more on it. And in my experience, I’ve seen most of retrospectives tackling those simple or at most complicated issues. And we’re skipping on reflection. And so the usual retro goes in by collecting data, hopefully, having some clustering or patterns looked at from the group, patterns, perhapse they are named, definitely prioritized. And then there are action items coming out of those parents discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a simplification of what a retrospective is like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the elements that I see happening over and over again, and were Cynefin can help is, okay, how can we fix this? So there’s this pattern, or there is this card? How can we fix it? And it’s a very linear kind of like, here’s the problem, how do we fix it. And that, in my opinion, does a disservice to our retrospective, by introducing Cynefin or other complexity frameworks, but in this episode we’re using Cynefin of an as a as a way to, to deal with this discussion when we generate insights, so after we gather data about their last iteration, we can use there is an activity called &lt;strong&gt;four points&lt;/strong&gt;. That doesn’t require you to introduce the framework first. So you have what they call a contextualized framework, based on the data that emerged from the last iteration. And what those four points are like, is basically four corners. And each corner has a sentence on the top left, we have situation is clear in retrospect. On the top right, we have expert could know the right answer. On the bottom right, we have everybody knows the right answer. And on the bottom left, there is no right answer. And in the middle, there’s an area where you’re confused and you don’t quite know where to put things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the the reason that we that I think this helps retrospectives is it moves on to a discussion where, okay, if everyone knows the right answer. That’s that’s fairly straightforward. And the expert knows the right answer is also something that we know where to go next. But the stuff that is sometime interesting is when stuff is clear in retrospect, and stuff is complex. And we need to run experiments and reflect a little bit longer than just jumping onto a solution that everyone knows. Now what I’ve seen happening here most of the time is, it’s clear to someone, but not to someone else. So if you cannot come to some sort of like agreement in in a timely manner, this is probably not as simple as that person thinks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, yeah, try it out. In your next perspective, I have an article that I’ll link in the in the show notes: &lt;a href=&quot;http://teotti.com/cynefin-helps-agile-retrospectives/&quot;&gt;http://teotti.com/cynefin-helps-agile-retrospectives/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And once you’ve determined like, Where are things living in those domains in those spaces, as yourself or us have the group ourselves, we’re what we want to tackle next. Use some sort of like a prioritization doc voting on what do we do? What do we want to tackle next, as well as what is in our area of control in our influence, so what is outside of the sphere of influence, and this is a space where it might be interesting to see things that are outside of our control and influence. What parts or sub parts are simple, complicated, complex or chaotic, and reflect on that and perhaps that helps generate some actions that are now within the area of control or influence of the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is about it for the five minutes of this short reflection on probably going to start following up with another one with some more practical examples of the probing that they Cognitive suggests you do in your complex spaces. Well thank you for listening, and until next time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/reflection-on-cynefin-helping-agile-retrospectives</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/reflection-on-cynefin-helping-agile-retrospectives</guid>
        
        
        <category>reflections</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Retrospectives Antipatterns</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this episode we have Aino, she’s a teacher, a technical conference editor and retrospectives facilitator. We’ll talk about 3 anti patterns from the book she wrote: retrospectives anti patterns,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/829735234%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-VJDC5EkCp8q&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;font-size: 10px; color: #cccccc;line-break: anywhere;word-break: normal;overflow: hidden;white-space: nowrap;text-overflow: ellipsis; font-family: Interstate,Lucida Grande,Lucida Sans Unicode,Lucida Sans,Garuda,Verdana,Tahoma,sans-serif;font-weight: 100;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/tirfpodcast&quot; title=&quot;This is retrospective facilitation&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;&quot;&gt;This is retrospective facilitation&lt;/a&gt; · &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/tirfpodcast/23-retrospectives-antipatterns-with-eino-corry/s-VJDC5EkCp8q&quot; title=&quot;23 Retrospectives Antipatterns with Aino Corry&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;&quot;&gt;23 Retrospectives Antipatterns with Aino Corry&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;about-the-guest&quot;&gt;About the guest&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/aino_corry.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Aino Corry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;short-bio&quot;&gt;Short bio&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aino Vonge Corry is a teacher, a technical conference editor and retrospectives facilitator. She holds a masters degree and a Ph.D. in computer science. She has 12 years of experience with Patterns in Software Development, and 10+ years’ experience with facilitation of retrospectives. For the past 5 years she has been focused on facilitating the agile journey for several companies in Denmark. She also teaches how to teach Computer Science to teachers, and thus lives up to the name of her company; Metadeveloper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Twitter: &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/apaipi&quot;&gt;@apaipi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Homepage: &lt;a href=&quot;http://metadeveloper.com&quot;&gt;metadeveloper.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://metadeveloper.com/retrospective-antipatterns/&quot;&gt;Retrospectives Antipatterns book&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/retrospectives-antipatterns</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/retrospectives-antipatterns</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Lessons learned in Retrospectives</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Paul is an agile coach, he’s helping expand and strengthen the Agile Coach Camp initiative, we met at the Retrospective Facilitator Gathering last year. I’ve asked him what his focus is in retrospectives given the recent shift to online plus lessons learned during his experience facilitating retrospectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/815384581%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-PEVftaYvtYk&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;about-the-guest&quot;&gt;About the guest&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/paul_boos.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Paul Boos&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;short-bio&quot;&gt;Short bio&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul is an IT Executive Coach with Excella helping managers and teams improve their game. He focuses on pragmatic ways Agile, Lean, and leadership techniques can be applied to create more effective organizations. Paul has led small teams to large groups as a Federal, commercial, and contractor software development manager and coached numerous organizations in the private and public sectors. As an active community member, he has founded several Agile groups, a government-centric Agile conference, and serves as the chair for the Agile Alliance’s Agile Coach Camp Initiative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Twitter: &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/paul_boos&quot;&gt;@paul_boos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;LinkedIn: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/paulboos/&quot;&gt;https://www.linkedin.com/in/paulboos/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;eMails: &lt;a href=&quot;pmboos@yahoo.com&quot;&gt;pmboos@yahoo.com&lt;/a&gt; (personal) &lt;a href=&quot;paul.boos@excella.com&quot;&gt;paul.boos@excella.com&lt;/a&gt; (work)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;blog: &lt;a href=&quot;paulmboos.com&quot;&gt;paulmboos.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/lessons-learned-in-retrospectives</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/lessons-learned-in-retrospectives</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A facilitation love story</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Gerardo has been a facilitator since 2004, now a board member of IAF he will tell us about his journey, different styles of facilitation, tips about affinity mapping and the upcoming mentoring program that IAF is starting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/795231730%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-NxbD9HgeJR9&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;about-the-guest&quot;&gt;About the guest&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/gerardo_de_luzenberger.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gerardo de Luzenberger&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;short-bio&quot;&gt;Short bio&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gerardo is a passionate and pragmatic facilitator and trainer. He has a dynamic personality, a great sense of humour and the warmth of real humanity. He combines the capacity to investigate innovative solutions with the ability to imagine and realise successful business ideas and promote new projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a degree in economics and a MBA, his professional career started as innovation project manager in a large no profit cultural organisation. Dealing with complex projects he discovered the importance of participatory project management and started to explore the world of facilitation and, of course, the Agile approach to project management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gerardo is a IAF – International Association of Facilitators CPF - Certified Professional Facilitator, and has got a certification on Agile Foundations from the Agile Consortium.
He is an assessor in the IAF CPF certification program and supports Agile transformations by training Agilists on facilitation. He works as a consultant and change facilitator for many different organisations, supporting their efforts in an Agile perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can find Gerardo’s contact details &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iaf-world.org/site/about/governance&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The book Gerardo referenced &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Everything-Miscellaneous-Power-Digital-Disorder/dp/0805088113&quot;&gt;Everything is miscellaneous&lt;/a&gt; in Italian &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ibs.it/elogio-del-disordine-regole-del-libro-david-weinberger/e/9788817039116&quot;&gt;Elogio del disordine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iaf-world.org/site/global-mentorship-program&quot;&gt;The mentorship program&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/a-facilitation-love-story</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/a-facilitation-love-story</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reflection on the retro on retros event</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/794510782&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome back for another short reflection episode. This time we’ll talk about retro on retros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, it’s a retrospective on how we run retrospectives. It might sound kind of crazy, or it might sound super interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, retrospectives are a time to pause, reflect and adjust. But they’re not static. There is no one size fits all retrospective. There is no checklist best practices that you can follow and get like a winning retrospective. It’s extremely contextual. And so there are practices that you can try and see if they work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if they don’t, you adjust, and a retro on retros is a time to do that kind of reflection. I like when I work with teams to do it with teams. But this event, this session that I’ve put online, so if you go to &lt;a href=&quot;https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/retro-on-retros&quot;&gt;https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/retro-on-retros&lt;/a&gt;, you’ll find a expression of interests where you can fill in your email, it’s going to be an event, an online event. And we’re gonna basically talk about our retrospectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, the way it goes is the same way, the same structure that any other retrospectives around and earlier said, well, there isn’t like a checklist to go through. That is correct, but there is still a structure like the what, so what now what adaptive action from ages the. And so retro retros will work the similar way. Again, it depends a little bit on how many people show up, but in general, it’s There’s a time for introduction to find out what everyone wants to get out of that session. so that everyone can kind of be present. In order to set the stage. Make sure that it’s a safe environment. So that’s another point. This session is for everyone. People with experience and people that are new to retrospectives. And everyone should feel welcomed and welcoming, and everyone always learned. learn something from from everyone else. So we we should all come in with that mindset. The first thing that we do then is start collecting anecdotal stories about our retrospectives, or topics that we want to discuss. I like to use the anecdotal format and to sell have the people add in their story itself signified our stories, and things like tags, for example. We can then maybe find patterns, find things that are in common, and again, depending on the size of the group, we might break into breakout groups or keep the conversation in one room and talk for 10 minutes about that cluster, that pattern that we see emerging. And maybe find some action items, some recommendation for those those contexts, maybe generate some insights, and then move on to the next cluster The next topic. In other cases, if we do breakout groups, the breakout groups might pick different topics, we might have tables and people discussing some of those topics. Again, it really depends on the on the size of the group, the biggest takeaway will be to bounce ideas off our peers. So if you find yourself alone, designing your retrospectives or you find that your retrospective doesn’t quite work the way you’d like it to. Maybe you feel there’s something weird about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might be a good session to join and to bring your your Your thoughts to the group there’s also the Slack channel so if you go to &lt;a href=&quot;https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/slack&quot;&gt;https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/slack&lt;/a&gt; you’ll find a free slack forum where you can ask questions and bounce ideas off peers. I’m looking forward to speak with you during the upcoming retro on retros. So go to &lt;a href=&quot;https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/retro-on-retros&quot;&gt;https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/retro-on-retros&lt;/a&gt; and fill in sign up for the for the newsletter.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/reflection-on-personal-retrospectives</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/reflection-on-personal-retrospectives</guid>
        
        
        <category>reflections</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reflection on personal retrospectives</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/793075123&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a short five minutes reflection episode. The topic is personal retrospectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been introduced to it for the first time in reference to Ainsley Nies. I think the concept is somewhat similar to the team retrospectives or group retrospectives that most people are familiar with. But they’re focused on yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And especially in those days where we spend more time alone at home. I’ve found it’s a good exercise to pause and reflect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So personal retrospectives, I think should follow the same approach of a regular retrospective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhat the five steps and again when we set the stage for our personal retrospectives is because we should think back what what are we trying to achieve? I think just the fact, for me, just the fact of reflecting on what I’ve done, what I’ve achieved is a thing that adds purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So sometime I focus too much maybe on the negatives. And so just giving myself time to look back at and just pause, just for like 10/15 minutes. And it doesn’t have to take more time than that. Another thing that that I like to do is to write down outcomes.So when I set the stage, I kind of prepare pieces of paper to put down possible action items. And then I look at the data. I use a system called GTD short for getting things done. I highly encourage you to look at it as a it’s just a way to track things that you’re doing by linking them to I think he calls them horizon different level objectives so that you don’t just do busy work, but you do things that are connected to some projects, and some something that gives meaning to you. But bottom line, I use GTD to find the items that I completed during the week. So for you, maybe you want to like spend a few minutes thinking back what happened during the week. And then maybe you can group some of those things and signify them. What made you happy? What made you sad? I think the tree comes approaches works pretty well for a personal retrospective, or whatever comes whatever hashtags perhaps you want to, to assign to some of those topics and of those patterns. And then do you see anything then spend a few minutes maybe like just thinking what if What if last week was perfect? What would be one thing that was different? Is there anything actionable out of that, that that you can do? You can use the SMART goal approach, like, Is there something specific, something relevant to you that you can do something achievable in the time and especially in the constraints that we have constraints that we can see, perhaps as enabling constraints to stretch our our boundaries of what we know and how we do things regularly. So out of that, you might come up with action items, things that you might do differently this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, to me the biggest value I find in personal retrospectives is to the time to pause and look back at the things that I’ve done during the week. And the things that are coming up next week. To see things in perspective, it kind of fills me up with a sense of achievement and reflection that allows me to maybe adjust the way I’ve done things this week in the in the week that is coming up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I hope that you’ll try out to do a personal retrospective. Try to maybe only spend like 10 minutes and write down the things that happened to you this week. And maybe then start assigning tags or find patterns and then maybe see if there is any adjustment that is is easy to do in the coming week. Let us know how your personal retrospective goes!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/reflection-on-personal-retrospectives</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/reflection-on-personal-retrospectives</guid>
        
        
        <category>reflections</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Imago dialogue to improve communication in your retrospective</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever experienced people in your retrospective talking past—or over—each other? In this episode we’ll tackle that with Karen Gimnig.  She has been using tools from the IMAGO technique for several years to improve group communication. She’s a brilliant facilitator, we met at an open space conference in Oregon where she did engaging sessions about this topic. She’ll explain us how to run that activity for our group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/783353650%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-zIDcZhGJf0f&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;about-the-guest&quot;&gt;About the guest&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/karen_gimnig.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Karen Gimnig&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;short-bio&quot;&gt;Short bio&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Karen Gimnig is a professional facilitator. She supports groups as they work together, and trains groups in the communication, conflict work and collaboration skills they need for effective and fulfilling work relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contact her through her website at &lt;a href=&quot;karengimnig.net&quot;&gt;karengimnig.net&lt;/a&gt; , by email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:gimnig@gmail.com&quot;&gt;gimnig@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;, or phone 678-705-9007&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/imago-dialogue-to-improve-communication-in-your-retrospective</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/imago-dialogue-to-improve-communication-in-your-retrospective</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Suddenly remote retrospectives</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this episode we focus on sudden remote retrospectives. What if you were used to physical retrospective and now your office is all remote? What are some tips for setting up an effective remote retrospectives? That’s the focus of this interview with Mark Kilby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/783166312&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;about-the-guest&quot;&gt;About the guest&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/mark_kilby.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mark Kilby&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;short-bio&quot;&gt;Short bio&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an agile coach, Mark Kilby has cultivated more distributed and dispersed teams than collocated teams. He’s coached as a consultant, an internal coach, and as a facilitator of distributed professional communities. His easy-going style helps teams learn to collaborate and discover their path to success and sustainability. See https://markkilby.com for his blog,  articles and information on his latest book, From Chaos to Successful Distributed Agile Teams: Collaborate to Deliver&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.markkilby.com&quot;&gt;Mark’s website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Info on virtual lean coffee:  You can read about lean coffee at &lt;a href=&quot;http://leancoffee.org/&quot;&gt;http://leancoffee.org/&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.markkilby.com/virtual-lean-coffee/&quot;&gt;https://www.markkilby.com/virtual-lean-coffee/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My book is available in print, e-book and audio on many platforms &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.markkilby.com/sdatbook/&quot;&gt;https://www.markkilby.com/sdatbook/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Link to our self-paced online courses including the free course for the rapidly remote - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.markkilby.com/workshops/&quot;&gt;https://www.markkilby.com/workshops/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/suddenly-remote-retrospectives</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/suddenly-remote-retrospectives</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Retrospectives are boring and useless</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Gitte share her insights on how to avoid boring and useless retrospectives. Remembering we operate in a complex adaptive system, themed retrospectives, external facilitators and more. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/776356180&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;about-the-guest&quot;&gt;About the guest&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/gitte_klitgaard.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gitte Klitgaard&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;short-bio&quot;&gt;Short bio&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gitte Klitgaard is an agile coach with more than a decade of experience working for companies as well as coaching individuals. She lives and loves agile, and hates turf wars, which is why she took the oath of non-allegiance. Why fight over methods, when we can use that energy to help people? Gitte wants to change the world by helping people work better together and feel better about themselves. She is known for speaking her mind in a way that helps people actually listen to what she says; maybe because her main working tools are listening and caring. As an active part of the agile community, Gitte often engages in discussion online and offline, and is part of the organiser team of German Agile Coach Camp as well as a facilitator at other events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She has great interest in how people function, how we communicate, how the brain works, what motivates us, how we can feel better about ourselves, and how to be perfect in our imperfections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working in different companies in Europe and developing training as needed, her expertise now centre on soft skills, as she has found this to be something missing in many organisations. The past few years she has been focusing on creating psychological safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2013 Gitte has been speaking and doing workshops, and keynoting at international conferences across three continents (mainly for developers, agile professionals and testers). Her talks are often about the topics we don’t talk about: stress, mental health, inclusion, vulnerability and courage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Follow Gitte on Twitter &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nativewired&quot;&gt;@nativewired&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Her blog post: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nativewired.com/retrospectives-are-boring-and-useless-or-are-they/&quot;&gt;Retrospectives are boring and useless – or are they&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/retrospectives-are-boring-and-useless</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/retrospectives-are-boring-and-useless</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reflection before world retrospective day 2020</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/774124156&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this short five minutes reflection I will tell you a little bit about the upcoming world retrospective day 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So world retrospective day is an event to spread the word about the benefits of retrospectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a worldwide event. And it’s self organized event. If you head to &lt;a href=&quot;http://worldretrospectiveday.com&quot;&gt;http://worldretrospectiveday.com&lt;/a&gt; you will find on the homepage, a link to the list of events for 2020. And in that list, you can find events that are located in in a city or online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one that I’m promoting is actually going to be online on the Pacific West Coast UTC minus eight. And you can find out more about that if you had to &lt;a href=&quot;http://wrd2020.thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com&quot;&gt;http://wrd2020.thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the events are meant to, again, promote retrospectives. And you can find more details on the on the homepage of wordretrospectiveday.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can tell you a little bit about the the events that I participated at during the last year. They are again, self organized, they can be a mix of people with different experiences. So if you feel like you’re you’re a newbie, and you don’t know much about retrospectives, they shouldn’t stop you from creating an event. By hosting an event, you might attract someone that is more experienced to share some of some of their stories with you. You can also do an online event like I’m doing. I live in Los Angeles and usually the commutes here are pretty bad. So I decided to now switch to an online event last year was a physical event. It didn’t go super well. I probably didn’t promote it very well either :D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So feel free to set up events if you don’t see one close to you. There’s also the whole coronavirus matter hitting us right now in the US around the world. So being conscious about avoiding avoiding group meetings is another reason to switch to online. So maybe you’re not familiar with online. So this would be like a good experience to set the event. Now, what would you do in a world retrospective Day event? I can tell you again, the the event that I organized is divided in an hour and a half of interactive activities and half an hour with a little bit of information sharing. So the first half an hour there’s going to be a what is a retrospective, what’s the purpose of it, kind of like the basics if you will, and then for an hour and a half, we’re gonna run depending on how many people show up. My current design for this for this session is to have a kind of like a lean coffee style, where we have people sharing anecdotes, or little stories that they want to get feedback or have questions about in terms of retrospectives. The group will run a poll, decide what is the most interesting, interesting topic or interesting topics. And then we’re gonna open up for an open conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And again, really, depending on the size of the group, we might do breakouts, if there is more than a handful of participants. So this might be a fun way for you to kind of like expose your
expose yourself and attract again, people that maybe have more experience or maybe feel that less experience so you can share your stories with with them and give back something to the to the community. All those events are obviously free and volunteer basis, as far as I know, at least the ones that I’ve seen and again, the spirit is to share good retrospectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So again, if you’re interested, head off to &lt;a href=&quot;http:://worldretrospectiveday.com&quot;&gt;http:://worldretrospectiveday.com&lt;/a&gt; and find an event near you. And if there isn’t one, just create one and contribute back to this community, to the growth and understanding of what retrospectives are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, thank you for listening to this episode. So this is like a new season. I’m gonna start publishing a bit more episodes coming up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;more-info&quot;&gt;More info&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http:://worldretrospectiveday.com&quot;&gt;http:://worldretrospectiveday.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wrd2020.thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com&quot;&gt;PST UTC-8 event&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/reflection-before-world-retrospective-day-2020</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/reflection-before-world-retrospective-day-2020</guid>
        
        
        <category>reflections</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
