<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>This is retrospective facilitation</title>
    <description>A Podcast interviewing thought leaders and experienced retrospectives facilitators.
</description>
    <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2020 18:20:16 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2020 18:20:16 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reflection on personal retrospectives</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/793075123&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a short five minutes reflection episode. The topic is personal retrospectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been introduced to it for the first time in reference to Ainsley Nies. I think the concept is somewhat similar to the team retrospectives or group retrospectives that most people are familiar with. But they’re focused on yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And especially in those days where we spend more time alone at home. I’ve found it’s a good exercise to pause and reflect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So personal retrospectives, I think should follow the same approach of a regular retrospective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhat the five steps and again when we set the stage for our personal retrospectives is because we should think back what what are we trying to achieve? I think just the fact, for me, just the fact of reflecting on what I’ve done, what I’ve achieved is a thing that adds purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So sometime I focus too much maybe on the negatives. And so just giving myself time to look back at and just pause, just for like 10/15 minutes. And it doesn’t have to take more time than that. Another thing that that I like to do is to write down outcomes.So when I set the stage, I kind of prepare pieces of paper to put down possible action items. And then I look at the data. I use a system called GTD short for getting things done. I highly encourage you to look at it as a it’s just a way to track things that you’re doing by linking them to I think he calls them horizon different level objectives so that you don’t just do busy work, but you do things that are connected to some projects, and some something that gives meaning to you. But bottom line, I use GTD to find the items that I completed during the week. So for you, maybe you want to like spend a few minutes thinking back what happened during the week. And then maybe you can group some of those things and signify them. What made you happy? What made you sad? I think the tree comes approaches works pretty well for a personal retrospective, or whatever comes whatever hashtags perhaps you want to, to assign to some of those topics and of those patterns. And then do you see anything then spend a few minutes maybe like just thinking what if What if last week was perfect? What would be one thing that was different? Is there anything actionable out of that, that that you can do? You can use the SMART goal approach, like, Is there something specific, something relevant to you that you can do something achievable in the time and especially in the constraints that we have constraints that we can see, perhaps as enabling constraints to stretch our our boundaries of what we know and how we do things regularly. So out of that, you might come up with action items, things that you might do differently this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, to me the biggest value I find in personal retrospectives is to the time to pause and look back at the things that I’ve done during the week. And the things that are coming up next week. To see things in perspective, it kind of fills me up with a sense of achievement and reflection that allows me to maybe adjust the way I’ve done things this week in the in the week that is coming up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I hope that you’ll try out to do a personal retrospective. Try to maybe only spend like 10 minutes and write down the things that happened to you this week. And maybe then start assigning tags or find patterns and then maybe see if there is any adjustment that is is easy to do in the coming week. Let us know how your personal retrospective goes!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/reflection-on-personal-retrospectives</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/reflection-on-personal-retrospectives</guid>
        
        
        <category>reflections</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Imago dialogue to improve communication in your retrospective</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever experienced people in your retrospective talking past—or over—each other? In this episode we’ll tackle that with Karen Gimnig.  She has been using tools from the IMAGO technique for several years to improve group communication. She’s a brilliant facilitator, we met at an open space conference in Oregon where she did engaging sessions about this topic. She’ll explain us how to run that activity for our group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/783353650%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-zIDcZhGJf0f&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;about-the-guest&quot;&gt;About the guest&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/karen_gimnig.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Karen Gimnig&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;short-bio&quot;&gt;Short bio&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Karen Gimnig is a professional facilitator. She supports groups as they work together, and trains groups in the communication, conflict work and collaboration skills they need for effective and fulfilling work relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contact her through her website at &lt;a href=&quot;karengimnig.net&quot;&gt;karengimnig.net&lt;/a&gt; , by email at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:gimnig@gmail.com&quot;&gt;gimnig@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;, or phone 678-705-9007&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/imago-dialogue-to-improve-communication-in-your-retrospective</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/imago-dialogue-to-improve-communication-in-your-retrospective</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Suddenly remote retrospectives</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this episode we focus on sudden remote retrospectives. What if you were used to physical retrospective and now your office is all remote? What are some tips for setting up an effective remote retrospectives? That’s the focus of this interview with Mark Kilby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/783166312&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;about-the-guest&quot;&gt;About the guest&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/mark_kilby.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mark Kilby&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;short-bio&quot;&gt;Short bio&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an agile coach, Mark Kilby has cultivated more distributed and dispersed teams than collocated teams. He’s coached as a consultant, an internal coach, and as a facilitator of distributed professional communities. His easy-going style helps teams learn to collaborate and discover their path to success and sustainability. See https://markkilby.com for his blog,  articles and information on his latest book, From Chaos to Successful Distributed Agile Teams: Collaborate to Deliver&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.markkilby.com&quot;&gt;Mark’s website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Info on virtual lean coffee:  You can read about lean coffee at &lt;a href=&quot;http://leancoffee.org/&quot;&gt;http://leancoffee.org/&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.markkilby.com/virtual-lean-coffee/&quot;&gt;https://www.markkilby.com/virtual-lean-coffee/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My book is available in print, e-book and audio on many platforms &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.markkilby.com/sdatbook/&quot;&gt;https://www.markkilby.com/sdatbook/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Link to our self-paced online courses including the free course for the rapidly remote - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.markkilby.com/workshops/&quot;&gt;https://www.markkilby.com/workshops/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/suddenly-remote-retrospectives</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/suddenly-remote-retrospectives</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Retrospectives are boring and useless</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Gitte share her insights on how to avoid boring and useless retrospectives. Remembering we operate in a complex adaptive system, themed retrospectives, external facilitators and more. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/776356180&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;about-the-guest&quot;&gt;About the guest&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/gitte_klitgaard.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gitte Klitgaard&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;short-bio&quot;&gt;Short bio&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gitte Klitgaard is an agile coach with more than a decade of experience working for companies as well as coaching individuals. She lives and loves agile, and hates turf wars, which is why she took the oath of non-allegiance. Why fight over methods, when we can use that energy to help people? Gitte wants to change the world by helping people work better together and feel better about themselves. She is known for speaking her mind in a way that helps people actually listen to what she says; maybe because her main working tools are listening and caring. As an active part of the agile community, Gitte often engages in discussion online and offline, and is part of the organiser team of German Agile Coach Camp as well as a facilitator at other events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She has great interest in how people function, how we communicate, how the brain works, what motivates us, how we can feel better about ourselves, and how to be perfect in our imperfections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working in different companies in Europe and developing training as needed, her expertise now centre on soft skills, as she has found this to be something missing in many organisations. The past few years she has been focusing on creating psychological safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2013 Gitte has been speaking and doing workshops, and keynoting at international conferences across three continents (mainly for developers, agile professionals and testers). Her talks are often about the topics we don’t talk about: stress, mental health, inclusion, vulnerability and courage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Follow Gitte on Twitter &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nativewired&quot;&gt;@nativewired&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Her blog post: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nativewired.com/retrospectives-are-boring-and-useless-or-are-they/&quot;&gt;Retrospectives are boring and useless – or are they&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/retrospectives-are-boring-and-useless</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/retrospectives-are-boring-and-useless</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reflection before world retrospective day 2020</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/774124156&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this short five minutes reflection I will tell you a little bit about the upcoming world retrospective day 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So world retrospective day is an event to spread the word about the benefits of retrospectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a worldwide event. And it’s self organized event. If you head to &lt;a href=&quot;http://worldretrospectiveday.com&quot;&gt;http://worldretrospectiveday.com&lt;/a&gt; you will find on the homepage, a link to the list of events for 2020. And in that list, you can find events that are located in in a city or online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one that I’m promoting is actually going to be online on the Pacific West Coast UTC minus eight. And you can find out more about that if you had to &lt;a href=&quot;http://wrd2020.thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com&quot;&gt;http://wrd2020.thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the events are meant to, again, promote retrospectives. And you can find more details on the on the homepage of wordretrospectiveday.com.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can tell you a little bit about the the events that I participated at during the last year. They are again, self organized, they can be a mix of people with different experiences. So if you feel like you’re you’re a newbie, and you don’t know much about retrospectives, they shouldn’t stop you from creating an event. By hosting an event, you might attract someone that is more experienced to share some of some of their stories with you. You can also do an online event like I’m doing. I live in Los Angeles and usually the commutes here are pretty bad. So I decided to now switch to an online event last year was a physical event. It didn’t go super well. I probably didn’t promote it very well either :D&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So feel free to set up events if you don’t see one close to you. There’s also the whole coronavirus matter hitting us right now in the US around the world. So being conscious about avoiding avoiding group meetings is another reason to switch to online. So maybe you’re not familiar with online. So this would be like a good experience to set the event. Now, what would you do in a world retrospective Day event? I can tell you again, the the event that I organized is divided in an hour and a half of interactive activities and half an hour with a little bit of information sharing. So the first half an hour there’s going to be a what is a retrospective, what’s the purpose of it, kind of like the basics if you will, and then for an hour and a half, we’re gonna run depending on how many people show up. My current design for this for this session is to have a kind of like a lean coffee style, where we have people sharing anecdotes, or little stories that they want to get feedback or have questions about in terms of retrospectives. The group will run a poll, decide what is the most interesting, interesting topic or interesting topics. And then we’re gonna open up for an open conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And again, really, depending on the size of the group, we might do breakouts, if there is more than a handful of participants. So this might be a fun way for you to kind of like expose your
expose yourself and attract again, people that maybe have more experience or maybe feel that less experience so you can share your stories with with them and give back something to the to the community. All those events are obviously free and volunteer basis, as far as I know, at least the ones that I’ve seen and again, the spirit is to share good retrospectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So again, if you’re interested, head off to &lt;a href=&quot;http:://worldretrospectiveday.com&quot;&gt;http:://worldretrospectiveday.com&lt;/a&gt; and find an event near you. And if there isn’t one, just create one and contribute back to this community, to the growth and understanding of what retrospectives are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, thank you for listening to this episode. So this is like a new season. I’m gonna start publishing a bit more episodes coming up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;more-info&quot;&gt;More info&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http:://worldretrospectiveday.com&quot;&gt;http:://worldretrospectiveday.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wrd2020.thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com&quot;&gt;PST UTC-8 event&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/reflection-before-world-retrospective-day-2020</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/reflection-before-world-retrospective-day-2020</guid>
        
        
        <category>reflections</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>An agile retrospective with the Beatles</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;No Paul didn’t do a retrospective with the Beatles, but the title seems to fit given the example he gave about a technique called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.crrglobal.com/orsc.html&quot;&gt;ORSC™&lt;/a&gt; (organization and relationship systems coaching). How you coach the Beatles is different then coaching John, Paul, Ringo and George individually. Paul shares stories about ORSC™ and his facilitation journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/774115765&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;about-the-guest&quot;&gt;About the guest&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/paul_tevis.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Paul Tevis&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;short-bio&quot;&gt;Short bio&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Tevis is a coach and facilitator. He partners with technical leaders who want to work as effectively with people as they do with technology. You can learn more about his work at &lt;a href=&quot;http://vigemus.com&quot;&gt;vigemus.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;contact-info&quot;&gt;Contact info&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/paultevis/&quot;&gt;Linkedin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/Vigemus-Consulting-1321281591381649/&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/vigemus&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/an-agile-retrospective-with-the-beatles</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/an-agile-retrospective-with-the-beatles</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Positive emotional attractor and negative emotional attractor in retrospectives</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“Emotional intelligence, hope, mindfulness, and compassion help a person reverse the damage of chronic stress and build great leadership relationships. The Positive and Negative Emotional Attractors inspire sustained, desired change and learning at many levels.” In this episode I’ll chat with Kevin Callahan that will tell us how to practically use PEA and NEA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/717152659%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-iO432&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;about-the-guest&quot;&gt;About the guest&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/kevin_callahan.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kevin Callahan&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;short-bio&quot;&gt;Short bio&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kevin is the principal of Interaction Agility, Inc. He holds a Masters Degree in Positive Organization Development and Change, along with certificates in Appreciative Inquiry and Emotionally Intelligent Leadership and Coaching from the Weatherhead School of Management at Case Western Reserve University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is an authorized trainer for the International Agile Consortium (IC Agile) and a member of a team of global senior practitioners designing the IC Agile Certified Expert - Enterprise Agile Coaching certification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;contact-info&quot;&gt;Contact info&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/kevin-callahan-mspod&quot;&gt;Linkedin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/positive-emotional-attractor-and-negative-emotional-attractor-in-retrospectives</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/positive-emotional-attractor-and-negative-emotional-attractor-in-retrospectives</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>More conversations on remote retrospective facilitation</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Together, Kirsten and Jay have specialised in enabling distributed teams to reach high performance, using a combination of adapted facilitation techniques, team coaching methods and Agile frameworks. In this episode we will chat about structures and challenges for remote retrospectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/716952244%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-dSAYu&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some sketches I took during the interview:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; src=&quot;https://www.easyzoom.com/embed/326ef519d965444c9e58c6ea645fed80&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;270&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;about-the-guests&quot;&gt;About the guests&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/jay-and-kirsten.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jay-Allen Morris &amp;amp; Kirsten Clacey&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together, Kirsten and Jay have specialised in enabling distributed teams to reach high performance, using a combination of adapted facilitation techniques, team coaching methods and Agile frameworks. In the last 3 years they have spoken at conferences on the topic of remote facilitation and creating effective distributed spaces, consulted to a variety of companies and provided remote facilitation training. They also host a monthly learning group to provide a space for facilitators to practice and share remote skills and techniques. Their book on remote facilitation will be published in June 2020 by US publisher Berrett-Koehler Publishers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;jay-allen-morris&quot;&gt;Jay-Allen Morris&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay-Allen currently works as a Delivery Manager at Woolworths online, where her focus is on developing agility and coaching teams. She loves finding ways of making remote spaces more human and engaging. This was inspired by working with distributed teams at her previous company Jumo, where she was an Agile Lead. She has worked in the agile space for over 5 years, coaching teams and companies to overcome their unique challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;kirsten-clacey&quot;&gt;Kirsten Clacey&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kirsten is currently working at eyeo, a fully distributed company based in Germany, as a Remote Team Coach. Prior to this she worked at Jumo as an Agile Lead and 22seven as an Agile Facilitator. Kirsten began her career in counselling and psychology and moved into software about 7 years ago.  She has focused primarily on the financial technology sector, working with both local and distributed teams. She’s worked with a range of companies, from those that are 6000+ people to small startups. She completed her honors in clinical and neuro-psychology and has built on her experience in counseling to enhance her effectiveness when coaching teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-to-contact-us&quot;&gt;How to contact us:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twitter: &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/remotebetter&quot;&gt;@remotebetter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:remotefacilitator@gmail.com&quot;&gt;remotefacilitator@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/more-conversations-on-remote-retrospective-facilitation</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/more-conversations-on-remote-retrospective-facilitation</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A retrospectives is where the action is</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Elise wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lucidmeetings.com/book&quot;&gt;Where the action is&lt;/a&gt; a book about meetings that make or break your organization. She’ll share some insights on how to make our retrospectives even more effective considering the meeting performance maturity model, core competencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/690323788%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-kmbWw&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;about-the-guest&quot;&gt;About the guest&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/elise_keith.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Elise Keith&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;contact-info&quot;&gt;Contact info&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our company website has contact info and a ton of great stuff on it: &lt;a href=&quot;http://lucidmeetings.com&quot;&gt;lucidmeetings.com&lt;/a&gt;
For speaking, interviews, etc, my personal website is: &lt;a href=&quot;http://jelisekeith.com&quot;&gt;jelisekeith.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;short-bio&quot;&gt;Short bio&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J. Elise Keith is the founder and CEO of Lucid Meetings, the author of &lt;em&gt;Where the Action Is: The Meetings That Make or Break Your Organization&lt;/em&gt;, and regular contributor for Inc. and other publications. Lucid Meetings provides services, software, and resources that help thousands of organizations worldwide implement a system of successful meetings.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/a-retrospectives-is-where-the-action-is</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/a-retrospectives-is-where-the-action-is</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reflection on picking a retrospective framework instead of activities</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/690322372%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-KKSQa&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this short reflection wanted to share my thoughts on picking a retrospective framework instead of activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very often, you hear people picking a sailboat retrospective or a tree columns retrospective. And those are simply activities, activities to gather data or generate insights. A retrospective framework is something like the five steps framework by Derby/Larsen, or ORID (objective, reflective, interpretive and decision).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, the good thing of picking a framework rather than activities is that you will have a structure for your retrospective meeting. And then you can tailor the activities based on the group situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to use the five step framework, which is the one I’m most familiar with, which has again, five steps. The first one is to set the stage. The second one is to gather data. The third one is to generate insights followed by deciding what to do and closing the retrospective. Now, those five steps are rooted I. They seem, I guess, the first time I heard of them kind of overwhelming. But the opening and closing is something that really should happen in any meeting. Opening sets the purpose. So opening set the stage sets the purpose, checks that the temperature and make sure that everyone is on the same page about the objective about what’s going to happen. So let’s jump the last one which is close, which is basically a stat to make sure is everyone everyone is on the same page about what’s going to happen after the retrospective, there was a critical steps, especially the clothes is is a time that you can gather a quick feedback on the retrospective itself. And again, it’s really critical, in my opinion, to save up 510 minutes, depending on the group size at the end. So opening and closing the two steps. And then in the middle, we have something that resemble the what, what So what now what approach where we look at the data. So data data is step number two in the five steps framework to make sure that everyone is on the same page about what happened, what happened in the last year ratio, what happened about the incident or topic that we’re looking at. So gather data, and then generate insights, which is a critical piece of all this. And jury insights, you could see it as a brainstorming. It’s a step where we kind of go into like, divergent thinking. And we try and come up with different ideas, we try and come up with different options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a way, if you if you imagine that you’re trying to, I often use this example, when I’m around workshop about this five steps is imagine that you’re trying to organize a vacation trip with your friends. And so that will be the purpose. So when you set the stage, we’re going to try and organize this trip together. gathering data will be looking back at your last trip. Maybe as individuals look at the data, think about the good and the bad. The things they would do differently. And the way you phrase this is really like dependent on the group. And generate insights is the piece where once everyone is on the same page about the past experience, they come up with new ideas about how would you like this next trip that we’re organizing to be different. So generate insights, this step where we come up with with different ideas with options about this, and this is a good time to also take a break, let your subconscious kick in and give you even even more, more ideas. And then decide what to do a time to kind of like put this, put this, this retrospective this meeting into into action, make something concrete out of it. So try and use SMART objectives specific, measurable, relevant, achievable, time bound, or whatever acronym that kind of makes the action. The decision actionable. And if you don’t have time, now’s a good moment to reflect on Hey, what’s the next step? If we don’t have an action plan, at least a step was the next step to move forward on this initiative. And then like I said, close out the last five minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;more-info&quot;&gt;More info&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/the-five-steps-retrospective-framework&quot;&gt;Listen to Diana Larsen talk about the framework on the podcast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Agile-Retrospectives-Making-Teams-Great/dp/0977616649&quot;&gt;Read the Agile retrospectives book&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pacific-edge.info/2010/08/orid/&quot;&gt;ORID&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/reflection-on-retrospective-frameworks-instead-of-activities</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/reflection-on-retrospective-frameworks-instead-of-activities</guid>
        
        
        <category>reflections</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
