<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>This is retrospective facilitation</title>
    <description>A Podcast interviewing thought leaders and experienced retrospectives facilitators.
</description>
    <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 12:31:30 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 12:31:30 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reflection on voting in retrospectives</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/646762749&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a new, shorter five minutes version of the podcast where I’m simply chatting a little bit about topics that the audience wants us to discuss online, or findings that I’ve got from my erection retrospectives. And today, I’m going to talk about voting and anonymous voting dot voting. Oftentimes, we have like a lot of topics that needs to be discussed in a retrospective people feel like they they want to be heard. But in the in the limited time sometime it’s one hour, sometime it’s half an hour, we need to prioritize. And I guess when the retrospective is co located, people tend to dot vote. And that can be leading in the sense that if we have three people already adding votes on certain areas or certain clusters, the following people voting, might feel compelled to make their vote count. So they probably wouldn’t put their votes on something that nobody else has voted. Or maybe they would, regardless of that one way that I found effective to prevent this situation, which is another one another one of those situation is like people waiting until the very end, so that they can be the one that make their vote count most, I guess. So one way to easily prevent, prevent this, as well as another way to, if you have like a group of like 15 people, and having everyone go on the board and put votes can be, can be a problem in terms of logistics. So the solution I’m about to suggest can kinda fix both situations one, where there is like voting leading. And the other one where it’s more on an organization issue… just put numbers on the topics that need to be discussed. And ask the audience to write on a post it note, say that you want to give them three votes, write down the three numbers of the topics that you want to discuss. So imagine you have this board with like five, 6, 10 clusters of topics, you would proceed and write a number next to that topic. And if it’s on a whiteboard, we’ll just put it on the whiteboard. If it’s in a post it note, it might be useful to put the number assigned to the topic on the post it note itself. And now we have a whiteboard with say then post it notes or 10 clusters with a number next to it. And now you can ask the audience well take three minutes to look around the topics. And now here’s a gotcha make sure that before people vote, they know exactly what those topics are. So before you go to the voting step, I’m assuming that you’ve already clarify with your audience, about what the topics are, everyone is clear on what we are going to discuss, and what the purpose of this discussion is going to be. But I guess that purpose and get it to the purpose might be might be for another for another short podcast. So once you give them the prompt, a find the three topics that you want to discuss, give them time to look around, and then they’ll write on their post it note the three numbers of the three topics that they want to discuss. So once that’s done, the best way that I found to collect these numbers is you as the facilitator, you go to a board and you say number one who voted for number one, raise your hand. And at this point, you do a count tally next number one, number two, and so on and so forth. And I found this is an effective way to, again, manage a room full of people. I’ve used this once with, we’re in this small room there were about like 10/12 people. And we had like, I don’t know, 10… 12, 15 topics on the board and having someone suggest Okay, now we go to the board and we start voting, the opposite would have been really messy. So okay, let’s put the numbers next to the topics. Let’s write on a post it note the number that we want to vote. Now, number one who voted for number one, who would have a number two. And the other way that this kind of like helps is to prevent that person or those two persons at the end to keep their votes so that the vote can count the most. Well, I hope you enjoyed this short five minutes. And let us know on Twitter, if you want, like specific topics to discuss in this short five minutes. Thank you and let’s see you on the next podcast.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/reflection-on-voting-in-retrospectives</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/reflection-on-voting-in-retrospectives</guid>
        
        
        <category>reflections</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Retrospective Facilitators Gathering (RFG) 2019</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this episode I have 4 guests: Veit Richter, Malte Sussdorff, Aino Corry, George Dinwiddie. I was with them and about 20 other folks in Massachusetts for a 5 days open space conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/640986156%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-PuLaw&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;regular&quot; src=&quot;/assets/rfg-2019-group-photo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;group photo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The retrospective facilitators gathering is a yearly open space conference–started in 2002–where we discuss retrospective facilitation techniques and everything that connects to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;regular&quot; src=&quot;/assets/rfg-2019-history.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Started in 2002 from a Norm Kerth idea&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would you spend one week on a conference dedicated to retrospective facilitation? I attended this year’s (2019) and in this episode I chat with 4 others attendees and we will tell you what we got out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andy–another participant of RFG 2019 who’s not on the show–wrote a detailed blog post of his experience https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/my-personal-retrospective-facilitator-gathering-2019-andreas-schliep/.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guests&quot;&gt;Guests&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/rfg-2019-guests.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Veit Richter, Malte Sussdorff, Aino Corry, George Dinwiddie&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;veit-richter&quot;&gt;Veit Richter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/veit-richter/&quot;&gt;Linkedin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;malte-sussdorff&quot;&gt;Malte Sussdorff&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sussdorff&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/sussdorff/&quot;&gt;Linked&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;aino-corry&quot;&gt;Aino Corry&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:aino@metadeveloper.com&quot;&gt;aino@metadeveloper.com&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/apaipi&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/aino-vonge-corry-9a23801/&quot;&gt;Linkedin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;george-dinwiddie&quot;&gt;George Dinwiddie&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/gdinwiddie&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; is the most immediate way to get hold of me. Websites http://idiacomputing.com and http://blog.gdinwiddie.com are good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music used in intro/outro is by Krakatoa https://krackatoa.bandcamp.com/album/running-with-wise-fools&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/retrospective-facilitators-gathering-2019</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/retrospective-facilitators-gathering-2019</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Preparing and facilitating a large retrospective</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Anita, Lukas and Pam  collaborated in facilitating a retrospective for multiple teams with a total of 60 participants. They split the group in smaller groups and used nested diamonds of participatory decision making (from Kaner’s book).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They wrote a detailed blog post https://www.agile42.com/en/blog/2018/09/05/how-we-facilitated-all-hands-retrospective-60-people-three-hours/ but I wanted to ask a few more questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would you embark on such an endeavor, what did they learn and what recommendations they have for facilitators about to handle a group this large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/637244664%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-VJkPA&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guests&quot;&gt;Guests&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/anita_lukas_pam.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pam Clavier &amp;amp; Lukas Klose &amp;amp; Siebold Anita&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pam&quot;&gt;Pam&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pam Clavier is a nineteen-year veteran of IT consulting. She learned the ropes working in Business Analysis, Project Management, Change Management and other Management Consulting roles. She is currently an Executive Program Manager, implementing a new IT delivery model using Agile and DevOps. She loves learning and loves to work in the Agile DevOps environment where she can learn something new every day while working with motivated and energetic colleagues. Pam has a PhD in Information Systems on a Business Intelligence topic. She is a certified SAFe Program Consultant (SPC) and has CBAP, PMP, CSM and CSPO certifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can connect with her on &lt;a href=&quot;https://ca.linkedin.com/in/pamclavier&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lukas&quot;&gt;Lukas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can be contact via &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:lukas@klose-coaching.com&quot;&gt;lukas@klose-coaching.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lukas is an agile coach and trainer. His career took him from tech startups in the 1990s to managerial engagements, and finally to agile coaching, where he has found his passion of helping organizations transform their world of work to be more meaningful while increasing productivity and their competitive advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lukas  also helped build and now teaches the Agile Leadership Program at UBC’s Sauder School of Business. This program consists of seven classes covering various aspects of agility, ranging from foundational understanding of agility to specialized knowledge about leadership, product management and scrum mastering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;anita&quot;&gt;Anita&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can be contacted via &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:anitaesiebold@gmail.com&quot;&gt;anitaesiebold@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anita Siebold is a dedicated, passionate IT professional with 25+ years’ experience. She has extensive experience as a program and project manager with wide ranging scope, everything from custom development, to COTS implementations and infrastructure upgrades with teams 5-50+ people. Her experience with ITSM process implementation and improvement resulted in a stint as the IT Support Desk manager. Anita made the transition from the more traditional waterfall project model to the Agile DevOps environment several years ago. She is now embracing SAFe in her role as a SAFe Release Train Engineer with her organization as it scales its agile practice. Anita is grateful for the transition and her new found role(s) as she finds continuous learning and servant leadership suits her values, personality and gifts very well. She is certified as a SAFe Program Consultant (SPC) and a SAFe Release Train Engineer (RTE). Anita has CSM, PSM I, CSPO certifications as well as certifications in applied leadership (JIBC) and agile leadership (UBC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music used in intro/outro is by Krakatoa https://krackatoa.bandcamp.com/album/running-with-wise-fools&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/preparing-and-facilitating-a-large-retrospective</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/preparing-and-facilitating-a-large-retrospective</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Beyond retrospectives using Toyota Learning Kata</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you ever find your retrospectives only handle business as usual items? It can do more then that and our guest today is Adam Light which for the last 5 years has been using Toyota Kata concepts to achieve that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/633462576%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-uvpXb&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guest&quot;&gt;Guest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/adam_light.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Adam Light&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adam is a results-oriented leader of programs and people with extensive agile transformation and project turnaround  experience. Directed program management at TransUnion; Led agile transformations for Starbucks, NWEA, Portland General Electric and others; Co-founded the Agile Fluency Project. You can find him &lt;a href=&quot;adam@sotechadvisors.com&quot;&gt;adam@sotechadvisors.com&lt;/a&gt; Twitter: &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/KnowledgeLean&quot;&gt;@KnowledgeLean&lt;/a&gt; LinkedIn: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.linkedin.com/in/adamlight/&quot;&gt;http://www.linkedin.com/in/adamlight/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music used in intro/outro is by Krakatoa https://krackatoa.bandcamp.com/album/running-with-wise-fools&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/beyond-retrospectives-using-toyota-learning-kata</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/beyond-retrospectives-using-toyota-learning-kata</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why would you write a book about retrospectives?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Why do we need another book about retrospectives? In this episode Pat tells us about the book he wrote in 2013 about retrospective facilitation and share some insights from his experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/622425459%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-PMQRM&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guest&quot;&gt;Guest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/pat_kua.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pat Kua&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick Kua is a keynote conference speaker, trainer and author of three books: The Retrospective Handbook, Talking with Tech Leads and most recently, Building Evolutionary Architectures. He is currently Chief Scientist and former CTO of the mobile bank N26 (Berlin, Germany). Formerly a Principal Technical Consultant at ThoughtWorks for almost 14 years, he brings a balanced focus on people, organisations and technology to optimise the flow of software. You can find him blogging at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thekua.com/atwork&quot;&gt;http://www.thekua.com/atwork&lt;/a&gt; and on twitter as &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/patkua&quot;&gt;@patkua&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music used in intro/outro is by Krakatoa https://krackatoa.bandcamp.com/album/running-with-wise-fools&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jun 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/why-would-you-write-a-book-about-retrospectives</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/why-would-you-write-a-book-about-retrospectives</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>War time US Navy debriefings and retrospectives</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the third of a series of special episodes where I interview former military war veterans–now working in tech related industries–to reflect on their war time after action review experiences and similarities with agile retrospectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this episode I chat with Dan Greene a former F18 Navy pilot. He tells us about debriefings and a culture of feedback that starts in training. I ask him how the debriefing concept translated to his career outside the military.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/621331068%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-7Jt9p&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guest&quot;&gt;Guest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan Greene is an accomplished sales leader and general manager with a talent for building deep connections with his teams and motivating them to achieve fantastic business results.&lt;br /&gt;
Over the course of his professional career, he has held a variety of roles in sales management and business leadership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/dan_greene.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Dan Greene&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;regular&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/dan_greene_deployed.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Joey&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After graduating from the United States Naval Academy, Dan served as a carrier-based Navy fighter pilot and director of operations for a number of different aviation units.  He left active duty in 2004 and earned his MBA at UCLA while starting his civilian career in the commercial aviation business.  He transitioned into the Tech industry in 2006 as a sales manager at Google.  Dan spent 6 years leading a number of teams and businesses at Google before moving to Twitter where he grew and led the US Sales team for 5 years.  He spent the last two years working at early stage software companies in focused on conversational A.I. and customer data infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan resides in Willow Glen, CA with his wife, Karen, his three kids, and his yellow lab “Scout”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music used in intro/outro is by Krakatoa https://krackatoa.bandcamp.com/album/running-with-wise-fools&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/war-time-us-navy-debriefings-and-retrospectives-and-continuous-learning</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/war-time-us-navy-debriefings-and-retrospectives-and-continuous-learning</guid>
        
        
        <category>military</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>War time US Army after action review and retrospectives</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the second of a series of special episodes where I interview former military war veterans–now working in tech related industries–to reflect on their war time after action review experiences and similarities with agile retrospectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this episode Jon Schneider a fellow Pivot working on the Java Spring team tells us about action items generated during after action review (AAR) in a war zone. He tells us how tactical cycles constantly changes and how the teams collaborated and used ingenuity to adapt and circumvent situations–only apparently–outside their control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/620796036%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-ENYBh&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guest&quot;&gt;Guest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/jon_schneider.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jon Schneider&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jon is currently senior engineering manager, Spring reliability engineering at Pivotal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;regular&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/jon_schneider_humvee.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jon deployed&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;regular&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/jon_schneider_deployed.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jon deployed&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While he was deployed he was gun truck platoon leader on the first tour, company commander and battalion s3 operations on the second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music used in intro/outro is by Krakatoa https://krackatoa.bandcamp.com/album/running-with-wise-fools&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/war-time-us-army-after-action-review-and-retrospectives</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/war-time-us-army-after-action-review-and-retrospectives</guid>
        
        
        <category>military</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>War time debriefings in the US Marine Corps and retrospectives</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the first of a series of special episodes where I interview former military war veterans–now working in tech related industries–to reflect on their war time debriefing experiences and similarities with agile retrospectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some teams often skip retrospectives. What happens when you skip a debriefing in a war-zone? In this episode I speak with Jon Hawkins a USMC war veteran–now Chief Marketing Officer at customer.io–and reflect about similarities between retrospectives and military debriefings.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jon and I worked together in NYC and I have a lot of fond memories about the time we spent there so I asked him to reflect about retrospectives similarities with war time debriefings. Specifically about placing blame and psychological safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/620342352%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-EWQ8K&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;regular&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/jon_hawkins_driver.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jon deployed&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;regular&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/jon_hawkins_jurry_rigged_coolant_collar.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The jurry rigged collant collar&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guest&quot;&gt;Guest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/jon_hawkins.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jon Hawkins&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jon is currently CMO of Customer.io (Customer.io is a marketing automation company used by subscription businesses of all types (SaaS, IoT, Subscription box, Media, etc) https://customer.io&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was Sergeant in the 2ND Amphibious Assault Battalion (based in Camp Lejeune, North Carolina). Combat deployment was in 2004-05 to Fallujah, Iraq which is located in the Al Anbar province. The tanks was called an amphibious assault vehicle (AAV) for short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music used in intro/outro is by Krakatoa https://krackatoa.bandcamp.com/album/running-with-wise-fools&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/war-time-debriefing-in-the-USMC-and-retrospectives</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/war-time-debriefing-in-the-USMC-and-retrospectives</guid>
        
        
        <category>military</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Retrospective learning with double loop learning</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you ever find your retrospective fixing low hanging fruit? What about the harder issues? In this episode we’ll hear about double loop learning with Joanne Perold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/613470474%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-zdEQs&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guest&quot;&gt;Guest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joanne Perold helps organizations develop software more effectively. He brings decades of development experience from electronic hardware and embedded firmware to business information technology. He helps organizations, managers, and teams solve the problems they face by providing consulting, coaching, mentoring and training at the organizational, process, team, interpersonal, and technical levels. Involved in the Agile community since 2000, he has helped groups ranging from a 6-person startup to a Fortune 100 company and a billion-plus dollar federal program, either directly or in partnership with other companies. He is the author of Evolutionary Anatomy of Test Automation Code and co-author of Patterns of Agile Journeys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/joPerold&quot;&gt;@joPerold&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;Joanne.perold@agile42.com&quot;&gt;Joanne.perold@agile42.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/joanne_perold.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Joanne Perold&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music used in intro/outro is by Krakatoa https://krackatoa.bandcamp.com/album/running-with-wise-fools&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/retrospective-learning-with-double-loop-learning</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/retrospective-learning-with-double-loop-learning</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The end goal of a retrospective</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;What’s the end goal of a retrospective? I am gonna give you a little spoiler the answer is not to put stuff in three columns and fix all the sad items. In this episode we’ll George Dinwiddie’s answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/607633776%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-vrgje&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;here-are-a-few-highlights-from-george&quot;&gt;Here are a few highlights from George:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get lots of different prospective on things, technical and human side are extraordinarily important for software success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use retrospective facilitation for the first time after coaching TDD for a while to get feedback and reflect on it. I facilitated a 6 people retrospective in our cubicle, someone brought to my attention that I hurt their feelings, was unsure on how to handle that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I felt like I needed to contribute content even tough I was facilitating&lt;/strong&gt;. Esther Derby has been a great mentor of mine. She was the first one that first invited me in 2009 to the Retrospective Facilitation Gathering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Depending on the retrospective we might have different end goals&lt;/strong&gt;. We start by setting up the theme. Which direction are we going? Maybe we’re trying to fix a particular symptom the team in seeing. Maybe in how to deal something long term, sometime on some external issue, what’s the next thing we want to accomplish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The way I define retrospective these days is “looking at the shared past together in order to make choices for the future”.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groups notice things and that helps others to notice. The things that come out are not the thinks they had on top of their head when they went in. The 3 questions are meant to get starter not the end point. A lot of scrum is simplified because it’s easy to teach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some people say we already know what’s wrong and how to fix it so we don’t need a retrospective.&lt;/strong&gt; But they arrived to that conclusion alone and not with the team. And other people may disagree or not interpret the symptoms the same way, they may think the cause of the symptoms is different. And you don’t learn this unless you dig in from multiple prospectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lot of people like to use the 5 whys to go to the root cause of something. In my experience nothing has a single root cause.&lt;/strong&gt; Any behavior that persistent has a feedback loop that maintains that. People move from 5 why to a fishbone diagram that allows for multiple root causes but if you dig deeper what’s contributing to each of them? If you look you’ll find &lt;strong&gt;reinforcing or inhibiting loops&lt;/strong&gt; within the team, the organization or elsewhere. Once you can visualize it maybe you can remedy. Counteract or balance it somewhere else. &lt;strong&gt;Causal Loop Diagrams come from system thinking&lt;/strong&gt;. There is a lot of books about it out there &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Fifth-Discipline-Practice-Learning-Organization/dp/0385517254&quot;&gt;The 5th discipline&lt;/a&gt; by Peter Senge and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/714348.Quality_Software_Management&quot;&gt;Quality Software Management: Systems Thinking&lt;/a&gt; by Gerald Weinberg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One of the first facilitation skills I often see is allowing people to voice their thoughts&lt;/strong&gt;. If you’re rotating facilitator maybe you can learn from each other. You don’t need a professional retrospective facilitator. I haven’t studied facilitation. I learn from some great facilitators.  You don’t need huge confidence facilitation skills to facilitate a retrospective. If group is trying to work together they will help facilitate and step in if you overlooked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe people say we don’t need a retrospective. We see a problem we see a solution. That’s true, don’t wait for the retrospective just do it. &lt;strong&gt;During the retrospective I say we need to look at it more deeply at what actually happened&lt;/strong&gt;. Looking together is the best tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focusing the goal of a retrospective is not always so narrow it preclude someone else’s topic&lt;/strong&gt;. But if it’s really important to someone that it should be included in the goal of the retrospective. In a team if an individual has a problem the whole team has a problem. The structure of a retrospective is not so rigid, if you’re on generating insights but realize you missed something we can go back to gathering data for some specific issue before you moving again to generating insights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Retrospective for groups larger then 15 people is where your facilitation skill get more critical&lt;/strong&gt;. You might struggle to have everyone on the same page. But you can get them more on that. One of the issues I see unwillingness to stick out from the crowd. Exercises when you write first and talk later are helpful. Ensuring it’s a safe environment is also especially critical in large groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The retrospective facilitators gathering is a small open space conference&lt;/strong&gt;. Runs for a week. Pretty open in topic. People get more deep in to the topic. Everyone there is a facilitator. I personally got a lot out of it. You get a lot of different viewpoints. A great change to disconnect from the world and seeing what challenges people are facing and learn from others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s by invitation first to the people that attended the previous year and then goes to the people recommended. People can contact me if they’re interested in early May this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;favorite-retrospective-activity&quot;&gt;Favorite retrospective activity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pick activities that would help a particular group in a particular situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I have no background on the team I used to use the timeline. But now my go-to is FRIM (FRequency IMpact) by Diana Larsen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;book-reading-right-now&quot;&gt;Book reading right now&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/611437.Making_Contact&quot;&gt;Making Contact by Virginia Satir&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;favorite-dish&quot;&gt;Favorite dish&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steamed crabs with melted butter and spices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guest&quot;&gt;Guest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;George Dinwiddie helps organizations develop software more effectively. He brings decades of development experience from electronic hardware and embedded firmware to business information technology. He helps organizations, managers, and teams solve the problems they face by providing consulting, coaching, mentoring and training at the organizational, process, team, interpersonal, and technical levels. Involved in the Agile community since 2000, he has helped groups ranging from a 6-person startup to a Fortune 100 company and a billion-plus dollar federal program, either directly or in partnership with other companies. He is the author of Evolutionary Anatomy of Test Automation Code and co-author of Patterns of Agile Journeys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/gdinwiddie&quot;&gt;@gdinwiddie&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;gdinwiddie@idiacomputing.com&quot;&gt;gdinwiddie@idiacomputing.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/george_dinwiddie.png&quot; alt=&quot;George Dinwiddie&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music used in intro/outro is by Krakatoa https://krackatoa.bandcamp.com/album/running-with-wise-fools&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/the-end-goal-of-a-retrospective</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/the-end-goal-of-a-retrospective</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-one</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
