<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>This is retrospective facilitation</title>
    <description>A Podcast interviewing thought leaders and experienced retrospectives facilitators.
</description>
    <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2019 18:23:29 -0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2019 18:23:29 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Positive emotional attractor and negative emotional attractor in retrospectives</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“Emotional intelligence, hope, mindfulness, and compassion help a person reverse the damage of chronic stress and build great leadership relationships. The Positive and Negative Emotional Attractors inspire sustained, desired change and learning at many levels.” In this episode I’ll chat with Kevin Callahan that will tell us how to practically use PEA and NEA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/717152659%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-iO432&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;about-the-guest&quot;&gt;About the guest&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/kevin_callahan.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Kevin Callahan&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;short-bio&quot;&gt;Short bio&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kevin is the principal of Interaction Agility, Inc. He holds a Masters Degree in Positive Organization Development and Change, along with certificates in Appreciative Inquiry and Emotionally Intelligent Leadership and Coaching from the Weatherhead School of Management at Case Western Reserve University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is an authorized trainer for the International Agile Consortium (IC Agile) and a member of a team of global senior practitioners designing the IC Agile Certified Expert - Enterprise Agile Coaching certification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;contact-info&quot;&gt;Contact info&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/kevin-callahan-mspod&quot;&gt;Linkedin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2019 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/positive-emotional-attractor-and-negative-emotional-attractor-in-retrospectives</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/positive-emotional-attractor-and-negative-emotional-attractor-in-retrospectives</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>More conversations on remote retrospective facilitation</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Together, Kirsten and Jay have specialised in enabling distributed teams to reach high performance, using a combination of adapted facilitation techniques, team coaching methods and Agile frameworks. In this episode we will chat about structures and challenges for remote retrospectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/716952244%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-dSAYu&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some sketches I took during the interview:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; src=&quot;https://www.easyzoom.com/embed/326ef519d965444c9e58c6ea645fed80&quot; width=&quot;480&quot; height=&quot;270&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;about-the-guests&quot;&gt;About the guests&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/jay-and-kirsten.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jay-Allen Morris &amp;amp; Kirsten Clacey&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together, Kirsten and Jay have specialised in enabling distributed teams to reach high performance, using a combination of adapted facilitation techniques, team coaching methods and Agile frameworks. In the last 3 years they have spoken at conferences on the topic of remote facilitation and creating effective distributed spaces, consulted to a variety of companies and provided remote facilitation training. They also host a monthly learning group to provide a space for facilitators to practice and share remote skills and techniques. Their book on remote facilitation will be published in June 2020 by US publisher Berrett-Koehler Publishers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;jay-allen-morris&quot;&gt;Jay-Allen Morris&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jay-Allen currently works as a Delivery Manager at Woolworths online, where her focus is on developing agility and coaching teams. She loves finding ways of making remote spaces more human and engaging. This was inspired by working with distributed teams at her previous company Jumo, where she was an Agile Lead. She has worked in the agile space for over 5 years, coaching teams and companies to overcome their unique challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;kirsten-clacey&quot;&gt;Kirsten Clacey&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kirsten is currently working at eyeo, a fully distributed company based in Germany, as a Remote Team Coach. Prior to this she worked at Jumo as an Agile Lead and 22seven as an Agile Facilitator. Kirsten began her career in counselling and psychology and moved into software about 7 years ago.  She has focused primarily on the financial technology sector, working with both local and distributed teams. She’s worked with a range of companies, from those that are 6000+ people to small startups. She completed her honors in clinical and neuro-psychology and has built on her experience in counseling to enhance her effectiveness when coaching teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-to-contact-us&quot;&gt;How to contact us:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twitter: &lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/remotebetter&quot;&gt;@remotebetter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:remotefacilitator@gmail.com&quot;&gt;remotefacilitator@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2019 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/more-conversations-on-remote-retrospective-facilitation</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/more-conversations-on-remote-retrospective-facilitation</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A retrospectives is where the action is</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Elise wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lucidmeetings.com/book&quot;&gt;Where the action is&lt;/a&gt; a book about meetings that make or break your organization. She’ll share some insights on how to make our retrospectives even more effective considering the meeting performance maturity model, core competencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/690323788%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-kmbWw&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;about-the-guest&quot;&gt;About the guest&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/elise_keith.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Elise Keith&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;contact-info&quot;&gt;Contact info&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our company website has contact info and a ton of great stuff on it: &lt;a href=&quot;http://lucidmeetings.com&quot;&gt;lucidmeetings.com&lt;/a&gt;
For speaking, interviews, etc, my personal website is: &lt;a href=&quot;http://jelisekeith.com&quot;&gt;jelisekeith.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;short-bio&quot;&gt;Short bio&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;J. Elise Keith is the founder and CEO of Lucid Meetings, the author of &lt;em&gt;Where the Action Is: The Meetings That Make or Break Your Organization&lt;/em&gt;, and regular contributor for Inc. and other publications. Lucid Meetings provides services, software, and resources that help thousands of organizations worldwide implement a system of successful meetings.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/a-retrospectives-is-where-the-action-is</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/a-retrospectives-is-where-the-action-is</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reflection on picking a retrospective framework instead of activities</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/690322372%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-KKSQa&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this short reflection wanted to share my thoughts on picking a retrospective framework instead of activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very often, you hear people picking a sailboat retrospective or a tree columns retrospective. And those are simply activities, activities to gather data or generate insights. A retrospective framework is something like the five steps framework by Derby/Larsen, or ORID (objective, reflective, interpretive and decision).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, the good thing of picking a framework rather than activities is that you will have a structure for your retrospective meeting. And then you can tailor the activities based on the group situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to use the five step framework, which is the one I’m most familiar with, which has again, five steps. The first one is to set the stage. The second one is to gather data. The third one is to generate insights followed by deciding what to do and closing the retrospective. Now, those five steps are rooted I. They seem, I guess, the first time I heard of them kind of overwhelming. But the opening and closing is something that really should happen in any meeting. Opening sets the purpose. So opening set the stage sets the purpose, checks that the temperature and make sure that everyone is on the same page about the objective about what’s going to happen. So let’s jump the last one which is close, which is basically a stat to make sure is everyone everyone is on the same page about what’s going to happen after the retrospective, there was a critical steps, especially the clothes is is a time that you can gather a quick feedback on the retrospective itself. And again, it’s really critical, in my opinion, to save up 510 minutes, depending on the group size at the end. So opening and closing the two steps. And then in the middle, we have something that resemble the what, what So what now what approach where we look at the data. So data data is step number two in the five steps framework to make sure that everyone is on the same page about what happened, what happened in the last year ratio, what happened about the incident or topic that we’re looking at. So gather data, and then generate insights, which is a critical piece of all this. And jury insights, you could see it as a brainstorming. It’s a step where we kind of go into like, divergent thinking. And we try and come up with different ideas, we try and come up with different options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a way, if you if you imagine that you’re trying to, I often use this example, when I’m around workshop about this five steps is imagine that you’re trying to organize a vacation trip with your friends. And so that will be the purpose. So when you set the stage, we’re going to try and organize this trip together. gathering data will be looking back at your last trip. Maybe as individuals look at the data, think about the good and the bad. The things they would do differently. And the way you phrase this is really like dependent on the group. And generate insights is the piece where once everyone is on the same page about the past experience, they come up with new ideas about how would you like this next trip that we’re organizing to be different. So generate insights, this step where we come up with with different ideas with options about this, and this is a good time to also take a break, let your subconscious kick in and give you even even more, more ideas. And then decide what to do a time to kind of like put this, put this, this retrospective this meeting into into action, make something concrete out of it. So try and use SMART objectives specific, measurable, relevant, achievable, time bound, or whatever acronym that kind of makes the action. The decision actionable. And if you don’t have time, now’s a good moment to reflect on Hey, what’s the next step? If we don’t have an action plan, at least a step was the next step to move forward on this initiative. And then like I said, close out the last five minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;more-info&quot;&gt;More info&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/the-five-steps-retrospective-framework&quot;&gt;Listen to Diana Larsen talk about the framework on the podcast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Agile-Retrospectives-Making-Teams-Great/dp/0977616649&quot;&gt;Read the Agile retrospectives book&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pacific-edge.info/2010/08/orid/&quot;&gt;ORID&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/reflection-on-retrospective-frameworks-instead-of-activities</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/reflection-on-retrospective-frameworks-instead-of-activities</guid>
        
        
        <category>reflections</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Retrospectives for organizational change</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Jutta wrote a book about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Retrospectives-Organizational-Change-Agile-Approach/dp/1499190255&quot;&gt;retrospectives for organizational change&lt;/a&gt;. In this episode I ask her what drove her to write the book and what challenges she faced facilitating retrospectives for organizational change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/669745193%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-AZQ5y&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;about-the-guest&quot;&gt;About the guest&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/jutta_eckstein.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jutta Eckstein&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jutta Eckstein works as an independent coach, consultant, and trainer. She has helped many teams and organizations worldwide to make an agile transition. She has unique experience in applying agile processes within medium-sized to large distributed mission-critical projects. She is the coauthor (with John Buck) of the book Company-wide Agility with Beyond Budgeting, Open Space &amp;amp; Sociocracy: Survive &amp;amp; Thrive on Disruption (abbreviated with BOSSA nova). Other books include Agile Software Development in the Large: Diving into the Deep, Agile Software Development with Distributed Teams, Retrospectives for Organizational Change: An Agile Approach, and Diving for Hidden Treasures: Uncovering the Cost of Delay in Your Project Portfolio (coauthored with Johanna Rothman).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jutta is a member of the Agile Alliance (having served on the board of directors from 2003-2007) and has been a program committee member of various US, Asian, and European conferences, where she has also presented her work. Jutta holds a Master of Arts degree in business coaching and change management, Master of Science in product engineering, and a Bachelor of Arts degree in education. She can be reached at &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/JuttaEckstein&quot;&gt;@JuttaEckstein&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/juttaeckstein&quot;&gt;https://www.linkedin.com/in/juttaeckstein&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&quot;http://jeckstein.com&quot;&gt;http://jeckstein.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/retrospectives-for-organizational-change</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/retrospectives-for-organizational-change</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reflection on roles in retrospectives</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/669743213%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-Rl2uh&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is another short reflection episode. And today we’re going to talk about roles during retrospectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re a facilitator, you probably might have found yourself in a situation where you’re trying to facilitate a conversation while you’re keeping track of the time for this session or activity. And you’re also like taking notes about what’s being said on a whiteboard. And that can be stressful, and especially when, when you have larger groups. Now, some of those roles can be assigned or can be a way to make the retrospective more engaging for your team. For example, timekeeping,”Who would like me a volunteer today to keep track of time for this activities?” Of course, as a retrospective facilitator, you should prepare your activities before your retrospective. And so you will simply hand over to the timekeeper, the list of activities and how long does activity should take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, other activities like taking notes also can be uploaded to volunteers in the group. And that’s even for tracking action items. And if you agree to use SMART action item–or any other way to make them more specific and measurable–maybe that person can remind the group “Hey, this action item is it like specific? And measurable? By when is it going to be done? Who is going to do it?”. So again, as a facilitator, you’re not alone. There is a group of people that you are facilitating for that can help with some of those activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And again, before the retrospective as a facilitator, you’re probably the individual that will go through and prepare a retrospective plan. But that can be perhaps Don pairing with someone else on the group. Perhaps someone that is interested in the facilitation role and eventually airing during the retrospective itself and ultimately have this person rotate as a facilitator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the retrospective, there’s usually action items. And again, hopefully someone part of the group took note of those. And there are specific, measurable, relevant time bound. And maybe we have someone else that during the week will make sure that those action items are follow true to keep track of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I hope this short reflection will help you in the next retrospective. As a facilitator remember you’re not alone. Maybe you’re a tech lead or a scrum master or a product manager but that doesn’t mean that you need to run the whole show. There is a team of individuals that are probably willing and excited to join you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/reflection-on-roles-in-retrospectives</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/reflection-on-roles-in-retrospectives</guid>
        
        
        <category>reflections</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Discovering retrospectives from the International Association of Facilitators point of view</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever heard of the International Association of Facilitators (IAF)? In this episode we interview Karen and Wiebke–two members of IAF–that run a workshop called “Discovering retrospectives” during the European Conference of the International Association of Facilitators in Milan. I’ve asked about the IAF mission and what insights experienced facilitators had about retrospectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/653734718&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;about-the-guests-karen-schmidt--wiebke-herding&quot;&gt;About the guests Karen Schmidt &amp;amp; Wiebke Herding&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together with Edith Steiner-Janesch, Karen and Wiebke co-hosted a workshop called “Discovering retrospectives: What can facilitators learn from agile retrospectives for our own practice and debriefings?” during the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iaf-world.org/site/iafeme2019&quot;&gt;European Conference of the International Association of Facilitators (IAF)&lt;/a&gt; in Milan. They work together as part of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cocreativeflow.com/&quot;&gt;CoCreativeFlow&lt;/a&gt;, a living system of facilitators and consultants that creates interactive spaces and opens up new ways for collaboration and change. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read more about the workshop in this blog post: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.onsubject.eu/blog/retrospectives/&quot;&gt;Retrospectives - a cocreated toolkit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;karen-schmidt&quot;&gt;Karen Schmidt&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/karen_schmidt.png&quot; alt=&quot;Karen Schmidt&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a project and leadership whisperer, Karen helps people to collaborate with courage, curiosity, and creativity to achieve outstanding results. In her 20 years management and consulting career, she has supported people in projects and C-level executives in all kinds of organizations across Europe. She connects project superpowers, leadership and facilitation skills with agile and positive change practices. She is involved in the agile community since 2011 and co-founded an open source community for people in projects &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.overthefence.com.de/&quot;&gt;“Over the Fence - Projects Newly Discovered”&lt;/a&gt;. In this context she co-created a “&lt;a href=&quot;https://overthefence.com.de/manifesto/&quot;&gt;Manifesto for Slow Thinking in Projects&lt;/a&gt;“, and two &lt;a href=&quot;https://overthefence.com.de/the-books/&quot;&gt;books&lt;/a&gt; that help people to co-design and lead human-centred projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/karen_ks&quot;&gt;@karen_ks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:karen@overthefence.com.de&quot;&gt;karen@overthefence.com.de&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;wiebke-herding&quot;&gt;Wiebke Herding&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/wiebke_herding.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wiebke Herding&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a facilitator and communications consultant, Wiebke helps mission-based organizations create momentum for sustainability. She is the founder and director of the change consultancy ON:SUBJECT, focusing on inspiring communications, engaging meetings and powerful projects. Her clients range from campaigning organizations and engaged businesses to governmental institutions and UN agencies. Wiebke is an IAF Certified Professional Facilitator since 2012 and served on the board of the International Association of Facilitators (IAF). She is passionate about building agency for the great transformation, and loves making things – be it beer and bread or furniture and textiles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/wiebkehere&quot;&gt;@wiebkehere&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/wiebkehere/&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/discovering-retrospectives-from-the-international-association-of-facilitators-point-of-view</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/discovering-retrospectives-from-the-international-association-of-facilitators-point-of-view</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reflection on voting in retrospectives</title>
        <description>&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/646762749&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a new, shorter five minutes version of the podcast where I’m simply chatting a little bit about topics that the audience wants us to discuss online, or findings that I’ve got from my erection retrospectives. And today, I’m going to talk about voting and anonymous voting dot voting. Oftentimes, we have like a lot of topics that needs to be discussed in a retrospective people feel like they they want to be heard. But in the in the limited time sometime it’s one hour, sometime it’s half an hour, we need to prioritize. And I guess when the retrospective is co located, people tend to dot vote. And that can be leading in the sense that if we have three people already adding votes on certain areas or certain clusters, the following people voting, might feel compelled to make their vote count. So they probably wouldn’t put their votes on something that nobody else has voted. Or maybe they would, regardless of that one way that I found effective to prevent this situation, which is another one another one of those situation is like people waiting until the very end, so that they can be the one that make their vote count most, I guess. So one way to easily prevent, prevent this, as well as another way to, if you have like a group of like 15 people, and having everyone go on the board and put votes can be, can be a problem in terms of logistics. So the solution I’m about to suggest can kinda fix both situations one, where there is like voting leading. And the other one where it’s more on an organization issue… just put numbers on the topics that need to be discussed. And ask the audience to write on a post it note, say that you want to give them three votes, write down the three numbers of the topics that you want to discuss. So imagine you have this board with like five, 6, 10 clusters of topics, you would proceed and write a number next to that topic. And if it’s on a whiteboard, we’ll just put it on the whiteboard. If it’s in a post it note, it might be useful to put the number assigned to the topic on the post it note itself. And now we have a whiteboard with say then post it notes or 10 clusters with a number next to it. And now you can ask the audience well take three minutes to look around the topics. And now here’s a gotcha make sure that before people vote, they know exactly what those topics are. So before you go to the voting step, I’m assuming that you’ve already clarify with your audience, about what the topics are, everyone is clear on what we are going to discuss, and what the purpose of this discussion is going to be. But I guess that purpose and get it to the purpose might be might be for another for another short podcast. So once you give them the prompt, a find the three topics that you want to discuss, give them time to look around, and then they’ll write on their post it note the three numbers of the three topics that they want to discuss. So once that’s done, the best way that I found to collect these numbers is you as the facilitator, you go to a board and you say number one who voted for number one, raise your hand. And at this point, you do a count tally next number one, number two, and so on and so forth. And I found this is an effective way to, again, manage a room full of people. I’ve used this once with, we’re in this small room there were about like 10/12 people. And we had like, I don’t know, 10… 12, 15 topics on the board and having someone suggest Okay, now we go to the board and we start voting, the opposite would have been really messy. So okay, let’s put the numbers next to the topics. Let’s write on a post it note the number that we want to vote. Now, number one who voted for number one, who would have a number two. And the other way that this kind of like helps is to prevent that person or those two persons at the end to keep their votes so that the vote can count the most. Well, I hope you enjoyed this short five minutes. And let us know on Twitter, if you want, like specific topics to discuss in this short five minutes. Thank you and let’s see you on the next podcast.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/reflection-on-voting-in-retrospectives</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/reflection-on-voting-in-retrospectives</guid>
        
        
        <category>reflections</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Retrospective Facilitators Gathering (RFG) 2019</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this episode I have 4 guests: Veit Richter, Malte Sussdorff, Aino Corry, George Dinwiddie. I was with them and about 20 other folks in Massachusetts for a 5 days open space conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/640986156%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-PuLaw&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;regular&quot; src=&quot;/assets/rfg-2019-group-photo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;group photo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The retrospective facilitators gathering is a yearly open space conference–started in 2002–where we discuss retrospective facilitation techniques and everything that connects to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;regular&quot; src=&quot;/assets/rfg-2019-history.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Started in 2002 from a Norm Kerth idea&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would you spend one week on a conference dedicated to retrospective facilitation? I attended this year’s (2019) and in this episode I chat with 4 others attendees and we will tell you what we got out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andy–another participant of RFG 2019 who’s not on the show–wrote a detailed blog post of his experience https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/my-personal-retrospective-facilitator-gathering-2019-andreas-schliep/.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guests&quot;&gt;Guests&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/rfg-2019-guests.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Veit Richter, Malte Sussdorff, Aino Corry, George Dinwiddie&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;veit-richter&quot;&gt;Veit Richter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/veit-richter/&quot;&gt;Linkedin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;malte-sussdorff&quot;&gt;Malte Sussdorff&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sussdorff&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/sussdorff/&quot;&gt;Linked&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;aino-corry&quot;&gt;Aino Corry&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:aino@metadeveloper.com&quot;&gt;aino@metadeveloper.com&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/apaipi&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/aino-vonge-corry-9a23801/&quot;&gt;Linkedin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;george-dinwiddie&quot;&gt;George Dinwiddie&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/gdinwiddie&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; is the most immediate way to get hold of me. Websites http://idiacomputing.com and http://blog.gdinwiddie.com are good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music used in intro/outro is by Krakatoa https://krackatoa.bandcamp.com/album/running-with-wise-fools&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/retrospective-facilitators-gathering-2019</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/retrospective-facilitators-gathering-2019</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Preparing and facilitating a large retrospective</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Anita, Lukas and Pam  collaborated in facilitating a retrospective for multiple teams with a total of 60 participants. They split the group in smaller groups and used nested diamonds of participatory decision making (from Kaner’s book).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They wrote a detailed blog post https://www.agile42.com/en/blog/2018/09/05/how-we-facilitated-all-hands-retrospective-60-people-three-hours/ but I wanted to ask a few more questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would you embark on such an endeavor, what did they learn and what recommendations they have for facilitators about to handle a group this large.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/637244664%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-VJkPA&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guests&quot;&gt;Guests&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/anita_lukas_pam.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pam Clavier &amp;amp; Lukas Klose &amp;amp; Siebold Anita&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pam&quot;&gt;Pam&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pam Clavier is a nineteen-year veteran of IT consulting. She learned the ropes working in Business Analysis, Project Management, Change Management and other Management Consulting roles. She is currently an Executive Program Manager, implementing a new IT delivery model using Agile and DevOps. She loves learning and loves to work in the Agile DevOps environment where she can learn something new every day while working with motivated and energetic colleagues. Pam has a PhD in Information Systems on a Business Intelligence topic. She is a certified SAFe Program Consultant (SPC) and has CBAP, PMP, CSM and CSPO certifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can connect with her on &lt;a href=&quot;https://ca.linkedin.com/in/pamclavier&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lukas&quot;&gt;Lukas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can be contact via &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:lukas@klose-coaching.com&quot;&gt;lukas@klose-coaching.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lukas is an agile coach and trainer. His career took him from tech startups in the 1990s to managerial engagements, and finally to agile coaching, where he has found his passion of helping organizations transform their world of work to be more meaningful while increasing productivity and their competitive advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lukas  also helped build and now teaches the Agile Leadership Program at UBC’s Sauder School of Business. This program consists of seven classes covering various aspects of agility, ranging from foundational understanding of agility to specialized knowledge about leadership, product management and scrum mastering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;anita&quot;&gt;Anita&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can be contacted via &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:anitaesiebold@gmail.com&quot;&gt;anitaesiebold@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anita Siebold is a dedicated, passionate IT professional with 25+ years’ experience. She has extensive experience as a program and project manager with wide ranging scope, everything from custom development, to COTS implementations and infrastructure upgrades with teams 5-50+ people. Her experience with ITSM process implementation and improvement resulted in a stint as the IT Support Desk manager. Anita made the transition from the more traditional waterfall project model to the Agile DevOps environment several years ago. She is now embracing SAFe in her role as a SAFe Release Train Engineer with her organization as it scales its agile practice. Anita is grateful for the transition and her new found role(s) as she finds continuous learning and servant leadership suits her values, personality and gifts very well. She is certified as a SAFe Program Consultant (SPC) and a SAFe Release Train Engineer (RTE). Anita has CSM, PSM I, CSPO certifications as well as certifications in applied leadership (JIBC) and agile leadership (UBC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music used in intro/outro is by Krakatoa https://krackatoa.bandcamp.com/album/running-with-wise-fools&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/preparing-and-facilitating-a-large-retrospective</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/preparing-and-facilitating-a-large-retrospective</guid>
        
        
        <category>season-one</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
