<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>This is retrospective facilitation</title>
    <description>A Podcast interviewing thought leaders and experienced retrospectives facilitators.
</description>
    <link>http://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2019 07:15:45 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2019 07:15:45 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Introduce change in retrospectives</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this episode we talk with Linda about introducing changes to our retrospective facilitation and how the latest neuroscience research can help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/563782692%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-09Kql&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;here-are-a-few-highlights-from-linda&quot;&gt;Here are a few highlights from Linda:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I wrote software for the Boeing 777 I was brought in to transition from Pascal to Ada but found a lot of resistors. They started writing Adatran because they were never convinced about the switch. You can’t bring a new language and just change how people think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We need to realise we’re all biased, and it’s impossible to look at the world from another person’s point of view. Instead we can make sure the group has diversity. Somebody that has a different point of view… a skeptic is someone that disagree with us and asks good questions. If we all agree we’re probably all sharing the same bias.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On changing retrospective format:&lt;/em&gt; You can’t change other people. You can listen to them and ask why they do what they do. Ask them to tell you. In that explanation things will come out. You can phrase it as an experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The message of Agile is that we’re learning. We do the best we can with what we know right now. Realizing how inadequate it is but it will move us forward.&lt;/strong&gt; The US is facing a political division the solution is hard but you can take baby steps and move forward. An example is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.better-angels.org&quot;&gt;Better angels&lt;/a&gt; an organization to de-polarize the US by listening to each other. You can always begin. That is a hopeful approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are a collection of patterns from Fearless change that are essential no-matter what you’re trying to change:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you have to care about it (Evangelist pattern)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;little tiny iterations (Just do it pattern)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how did that work (reflection pattern)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;build on that (small successes pattern)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;move forward (baby steps pattern)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;we later found out that’s call the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.simplypsychology.org/learning-kolb.html&quot;&gt;Kolb learning cycle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Legacy system was gonna die the company wanted the new project to succeeded costed lots of money and produced nothing. What is we can do to learn something from this? How to make sure it doesn’t happen again? Norm Kerth was writing his book on Project retrospectives so he help me, he was generous and shared his wisdom and ideas on how do you learn from success and failures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I was learning I started going to the Retrospective Facilitator Gathering and learn–implicit knowledge instead of explicit learning–more about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the very first retrospective the primary thing I avoided talking about the project failure. It would have been valuable for them to talk about it but that’s what I knew then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without retrospectives a company would have big knowledge holes about what happens. When you’re introducing retrospectives for the first time I would not advertise that I don’t know very much. If you’re too forthcoming and honest and say you don’t know that much other people will think “oh you don’t know what you’re doing” and you won’t have credibility. Don’t lie about what you know but don’t bring it out because we all start that way. Just do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a pattern “pick your battles” to realize that sometimes it’s not the right time. Maybe people were not ready for it, or you or the company. If it’s not going well just wait and then you should try again. Because the context–people, you, the company–keeps changing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a fan of continuous retrospective. Don’t wait for the retrospective to remember what happened instead people can add items to a timeline as events happen. Adding the items and letting system 2–your subconscious–kick in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;System 1 and system 2 is from “Thinking fast and thinking slow”. A behavioral model for how the brain operates. System 1–the unconscious–is System 2–the conscious. System 1 is fast system 2 is slow. System 1 can remember a lot, system 2 is very forgetful. System 2 is the limited logical part of our brain. System 1 can work while we sleep… it’s a background process. Don’t waste time trying to come up with things, hand it over to system 1. System 1 is biased and it needs a sensor or a driver that’s system 2. Neuroscience fits better with a continuous retrospectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t use system 1 on command you can’t force it or you can’t predict. But you also can’t just sit in a room to wait for a great idea to come up via system 2. You can do it now and produce something that is not very good or wait until tomorrow and have a great idea. Sometime I hear “we’re not leaving this room until the discussion is done”, there is evidence that taking a break before the decision is made there are better outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5 whys is such a waste of time. System 2 can make up a reason and it has no clue, system 1 knows much more but there is no way you can just inquire it in real time. What you get is system 2 rationalization. You don’t get any closer to the truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the exciting thing about cognitive neuroscience. What we know now compared to what we knew 2 years ago is definitely changing and has impacts on what we do. I don’t force anything. If I need to give a talk at a conference or at a company I collect the context and then leave it. Hours later something happens. I know what I should do and put it together. Instead of forcing it, sit down and get it done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;favourite-retrospective-activity&quot;&gt;Favourite retrospective activity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Offer appreciations. I have dozens of stories. It can be implemented in many different ways. But everyone was a hero in the last iteration. Sit there until we’re all done, at the end people that were unhappy, unsure if they wanted to be on the team or not will feel different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;book-i-am-reading&quot;&gt;Book I am reading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Gut-Feelings-Intelligence-Gerd-Gigerenzer/dp/0143113763&quot;&gt;Gut feelings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;favourite-dish&quot;&gt;Favourite dish&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have one… but since this was recorded around Christmas, it’s a nutbread my mum used to make and reminds me of her. &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/Ruths_Fruitcake.docx&quot;&gt;Download the recipe of Linda’s fruitcake&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guest&quot;&gt;Guest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linda Rising is an independent consultant who lives near Nashville, Tennessee. Linda has a Ph.D. from Arizona State University in object-based design metrics. Her background includes university teaching as well as work in industry in telecommunications, avionics, and tactical weapons systems. She is an internationally known presenter on topics related to agile development, patterns, retrospectives, the change process, and the connection between the latest neuroscience and software development. Linda is the author of numerous articles and five books. The latest, More Fearless Change, co-authored with Mary Lynn Manns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/risinglinda&quot;&gt;@risinglinda&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://lindarising.org&quot;&gt;http://lindarising.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/linda_rising.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Linda Rising&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/3-introduce-change</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/3-introduce-change</guid>
        
        
        <category>season one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Becoming a facilitator</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this episode we talk with Ryan Latta about his journey becoming a retrospective facilitator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/585584835%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-l8kHp&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ryan shares some challenges he faced of running retrospectives and when he discovered facilitating retrospectives is more then adding items to three columns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;here-are-a-few-highlights-from-ryan&quot;&gt;Here are a few highlights from Ryan:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Before my scrum master went to retrospective facilitation training we always had a retrospective with 3 columns&lt;/strong&gt;–what went well, what didn’t go so well, what we want to change–dot vote and create action item. After the training I saw a more effective format and activity that digged topics deeper then the 3 columns. That’s when I realized there is a lot more to retrospective then what I first tought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Action items look similar but the journey that got to produce the action item has so much meaning to the team that the team doesn’t really need to know the action item exists. I don’t need to put it on a wall or in a backlog it just naturally happens and gets done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every single retrospective the team came up with action items. Before they tought this was a time set aside to complain but now are so much better they said. Why I asked? They listed all the action items for the last 7 retrospectives (5 months). What is that happens I asked? They created a set of rules for how to run a retrospective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hinge points of a retrospective is generating insights. That’s the part where teams create meaning. Far too much of a hurry in getting to an action item. Be intentional about creating time for the team to create meaning about what they do. One action item is better then 3 that nobody will do. I have the group go trough divergent opinions–casting the net very wide–then the act of converging is distilling all that down to the ones we want to invest in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In my retrospectives I don’t ask for perfect and definitive instead I ask for likely and plausible.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ask to prioritize to get to a focus for the retrospective. I often ask debriefing questions: “what about this was challenging?”, “what did we miss?” leading in to the final question “what’s the meaning of all this?” and see what they say. If the group agree that’s the insight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This group I worked with was not working well togheter–I understood there were emotions involved–when we went trough mad/sad/glad but there were F-Bombs dropped people crying. I asked them if everyone was working with good intentions, and the best job they could. So I asked if all this hurt wasn’t because we wanted to hurst one another but rather because things didn’t go well. People agreed. I asked if that’s ok to apologies for the hurt. The group did and after that things started getting better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Given what I know now I would have paid more attention to what is about to walk in that room talk more to these people before the retrospective&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I prepare for a retrospective because the group deserves that. I spend up to 1 hour to prepare a retrospective that is right for them at that time. I plan not to control it but to be prepared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retrospectives must be a safe space. When a facilitator hold power over the team–ie. a manager or a product owner–I reccomand to reflect on hot to begin the retrospective. For example look at &lt;a href=&quot;http://retrospectivewiki.org/index.php?title=The_Prime_Directive&quot;&gt;Kerth’s prime directive&lt;/a&gt; burn it in to their heart and then do a safety check.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When a room is full of individual that feel unsafe I run all the activities anonymously and dig in to what do you think has to change for the safety to change&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t care who facilitates. I think rotating facilitator is often because facilitation is not acknowledged as a skill. If people want to learn facilitation skills it’s fine to have them rotate in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team has to give permissions for managers and stakeholders to be present during team retrospective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;whats-your-favourite-retrospective-activity&quot;&gt;What’s your favourite retrospective activity?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mad, sad glad&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jean Tabaka’s sailboat&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mindmap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;whats-a-book-your-reading-now&quot;&gt;What’s a book your reading now?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Habits-Highly-Effective-People-Powerful/dp/0743269519&quot;&gt;7 habits of higly effective people&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;thinking fast and thinking slow review&quot;&gt;Thinking fast and thinking slow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Martian-Andy-Weir/dp/0553418025&quot;&gt;The martian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;whats-your-favourite-dish&quot;&gt;What’s your favourite dish?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tacos with veggies. A really well made steak. Pizza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guest&quot;&gt;Guest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ryan Latta has been building software and teams for nearly 10 years now. He currently works as an agile coach and scrum master with a mission of creating teams that change the world. He has had the pleasure of working in a number of industries including: banking, video game, education, advertising, and automotive. When he isn’t spending time with his family, he is mentoring new developers in starting their careers, playing games, and learning to play the fiddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/recursivefaults&quot;&gt;@recursivefaults&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ryanlatta.com&quot;&gt;http://www.ryanlatta.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/ryan_latta.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ryan Latta&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2019 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/2-becoming-a-facilitator</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/2-becoming-a-facilitator</guid>
        
        
        <category>season one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What is a retrospective</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this first episode we talk with Esther Derby about what a retrospective really is and the role of the facilitator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/575725029%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-KXZeI&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered what a retrospective really is? What’s the role of the facilitator? Is it just to pick an activity… time box discussions, move on to the next item… write down the action items and assign it to someone? Well if only retrospective facilitation was that simple… what are things to watch out for? What are things to strive for? In this initial episode we invited Esther Derby to answer some of these questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;here-are-a-few-highlights-from-esther&quot;&gt;Here are a few highlights from Esther:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started my career as a programmer, and I wore many hats since then: team lead, testing, dev-manager. Facilitation served me well in all these roles. I started doing Weinberg style technical reviews where a lot of attention was dedicated to ensure it was safe to talk about the code without criticizing the person that wrote the code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A retrospective is a special meeting for the team to learn and find agency so that they can take risks on their own behalf and make their worklife better&lt;/strong&gt;. Often people outside the Information Technology and agile space think about art retrospectives where you look at an artist’s body of work or past body of work. That’s what we do when we look at a team work–so people can understand patterns and how their action affect outcomes and how collaborate so they can make changes and better product. It’s about continuous improvement with agency rests in the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The role of the retrospective facilitator is to create an environment and a process so the team can have the discussion they need to have. Not all retrospective require a facilitator but all retrospectives do require some facilitation–oftentime by someone in the group that has those skills: thinking about a process to help learn and decide together, understanding the underpinning of the 5 steps retrospective:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set focus / stage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diverge to expand the pool of knowledge (Gather data)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Converge (Generate insights)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decide what to do&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Close&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Often groups converge prematurely producing habitual or not very deep thinking… just comfortable thinking that do not get to the real problem. This is an issue particularly in cultures that value deciciveness and speed. Part of the facilitation is to slow the group so they can diverge and develop insights and make decisions.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the signs a retrospective is not working are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there is no outcome or there is an “outcome” that nobody believe in&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if there is very little participation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if they are always talking about the same thing–that might be a problem with the facilitation or with a pressured environment that doesn’t give enough time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Without a retrospective a team might not be able to develop a sense of agency&lt;/strong&gt;. A sense of agency is a term that come from psicology and means “I can act on my own behalf”. I see a lot of workplaces where people are tought to be passive and need to ask for permission for so many things that they assume they have to ask for permissions for everything. When teams believe only the system–i.e. a commitee–drives the behaviour that can lead to passivity like “oh we can’t change it, it’s the system” but there are always things we can change to impact the environment and make it more conducive to the work you do. &lt;strong&gt;If nothing else you can always change your response.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked with a group that couldn’t change the process that was mandated–and only changed–by a certain group. So they changed how they responded to that when something wasn’t working. So the group developed a way to influence the committee that could change things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another group the VP would barge in and create more stories in the middle of the sprint. The group could not lock the VP out so they changed how they responded to that and developed a little script. When the VP would come in with more stories everyone would repeat the same sentence: “we understand that’s important to you, what should we take off the sprint in order to accomplish that?”. They would just repeat that. Eventually that changed his behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An activity to identify what’s in our control is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.innovationgames.com/circles-and-soup/&quot;&gt;Circles and soup&lt;/a&gt;, what we can influence and what’s in the soup. &lt;strong&gt;One of the things we can always control is our response&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use the 5 steps format for 90% of the retrospective I work on because it mirrors a tought process: focus, diverge, converge. It takes advantage of how people think when they think clearly. I’ve been in organizations when retrospectives started as a list of opinions (what did we do well, what shall we do differently), dot voting. That’s not a bad part of a retro but it’s not sufficient. I start where they are and slow things down. I usually ask if there is a focus for this particular week instead of just a laundry list. If they’re deciding what to focus on during the retrospective there is little opportunity to gather objective data. Deciding what to talk about and being hampered cause there is no more time. Objective and subjective data are equally important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t object to occasionally use retrospective to chill as long as this is not happening is all retrospectives and as long as it’s not a place where people prepare their grocery lists for weekend shopping. That tells me people aren’t finding anything useful in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having an agenda ahead of time and the topic helps people. If I am concerned about safety I’ll spend more time on tackling that and then gently introduce the new format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Developers can facilitate their team retrospectives&lt;/strong&gt;. If you’re part of the team and also the facilitator you need to make real clear which hat you’re wearing. I am reluctant in having managers facilitating retrospectives unless it’s a completely safe environment. Having some facilitation training is really important, I like the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ica-international.org/icas-technology-of-participation-top/&quot;&gt;technology of participation&lt;/a&gt; methods that came out of the work of the ICA (Institute for Cultural Affairs) so they tested these facilitation around the world. I prefer that to training that focus on specific tecquiques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can fit the 5 steps in 15 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;set the stage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gather data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;generate insights&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;decide what to do&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;close out (a retrospective on the retrospective)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The retro on retrospective only takes a few minutes and it’s a signal that anything can be reflected on including the retrospective.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on the situation I might put more time on one step rather then another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some traits important to retrospective facilitation are: staying out of the content, patience–people think at different speeds, empathy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A team that’s been doing retrospectives and is familiar with agency they may come up with a focus during the retrospective. I find with teams that are not accustomed to work this way it helps to have an agile coach choose a focus before the retrospective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;favourite-retrospective-activity&quot;&gt;Favourite retrospective activity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have one. The favourite is the one that works with the team I am working with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;book-i-am-reading&quot;&gt;Book I am reading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Michelle Obama’s biography&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accounting for Slavery&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Norman Invasion of England&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;favourite-dish&quot;&gt;Favourite dish&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Varies by season and by year, braised beef with wine and lot of polenta and pecorino.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guest&quot;&gt;Guest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Esther Derby is co-author of Agile Retrospectives: Making Good Teams Great, an expert in organizational dynamics, she teaches workshops and speak to groups and conferences all over the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/estherderby&quot;&gt;@estherderby&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.estherderby.com&quot;&gt;http://www.estherderby.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/esther_derby.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Esther Derby&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2019 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/1-what-is-a-retrospective</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/1-what-is-a-retrospective</guid>
        
        
        <category>season one</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
