<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>This is retrospective facilitation</title>
    <description>A Podcast interviewing thought leaders and experienced retrospectives facilitators.
</description>
    <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2019 22:37:23 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 May 2019 22:37:23 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>War time debriefings in the US Marine Corp and retrospectives</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the first of a series of special episodes where I interview former military war veterans–now working in tech related industries–to reflect on their war time debriefing experiences and similarities with agile retrospectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some teams often skip retrospectives. What happens when you skip a debriefing in a war-zone? In this episode I speak with Jon Hawkins a USMC war veteran–now Chief Marketing Officer at customer.io–and reflect about similarities between retrospectives and military debriefings.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jon and I worked together in NYC and I have a lot of fond memories about the time we spent there so I asked him to reflect about retrospectives similarities with war time debriefings. Specifically about placing blame and psychological safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/620342352%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-EWQ8K&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;regular&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/jon_hawkins_driver.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jon deployed&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;regular&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/jon_hawkins_jurry_rigged_coolant_collar.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The jurry rigged collant collar&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guest&quot;&gt;Guest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/jon_hawkins.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Jon Hawkins&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jon is currently CMO of Customer.io (Customer.io is a marketing automation company used by subscription businesses of all types (SaaS, IoT, Subscription box, Media, etc) https://customer.io&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was Sergeant in the 2ND Amphibious Assault Battalion (based in Camp Lejeune, North Carolina). Combat deployment was in 2004-05 to Fallujah, Iraq which is located in the Al Anbar province. The tanks was called an amphibious assault vehicle (AAV) for short.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/war-time-debriefing-in-the-USMC-and-retrospectives</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/war-time-debriefing-in-the-USMC-and-retrospectives</guid>
        
        
        <category>military</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Retrospective learning with double loop learning</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Do you ever find your retrospective fixing low hanging fruit? What about the harder issues? In this episode we’ll hear about double loop learning with Joanne Perold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/613470474%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-zdEQs&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guest&quot;&gt;Guest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joanne Perold helps organizations develop software more effectively. He brings decades of development experience from electronic hardware and embedded firmware to business information technology. He helps organizations, managers, and teams solve the problems they face by providing consulting, coaching, mentoring and training at the organizational, process, team, interpersonal, and technical levels. Involved in the Agile community since 2000, he has helped groups ranging from a 6-person startup to a Fortune 100 company and a billion-plus dollar federal program, either directly or in partnership with other companies. He is the author of Evolutionary Anatomy of Test Automation Code and co-author of Patterns of Agile Journeys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/joPerold&quot;&gt;@joPerold&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;Joanne.perold@agile42.com&quot;&gt;Joanne.perold@agile42.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/joanne_perold.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Joanne Perold&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/retrospective-learning-with-double-loop-learning</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/retrospective-learning-with-double-loop-learning</guid>
        
        
        <category>season one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The end goal of a retrospective</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;What’s the end goal of a retrospective? I am gonna give you a little spoiler the answer is not to put stuff in three columns and fix all the sad items. In this episode we’ll George Dinwiddie’s answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/607633776%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-vrgje&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;here-are-a-few-highlights-from-george&quot;&gt;Here are a few highlights from George:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get lots of different prospective on things, technical and human side are extraordinarily important for software success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use retrospective facilitation for the first time after coaching TDD for a while to get feedback and reflect on it. I facilitated a 6 people retrospective in our cubicle, someone brought to my attention that I hurt their feelings, was unsure on how to handle that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I felt like I needed to contribute content even tough I was facilitating&lt;/strong&gt;. Esther Derby has been a great mentor of mine. She was the first one that first invited me in 2009 to the Retrospective Facilitation Gathering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Depending on the retrospective we might have different end goals&lt;/strong&gt;. We start by setting up the theme. Which direction are we going? Maybe we’re trying to fix a particular symptom the team in seeing. Maybe in how to deal something long term, sometime on some external issue, what’s the next thing we want to accomplish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The way I define retrospective these days is “looking at the shared past together in order to make choices for the future”.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groups notice things and that helps others to notice. The things that come out are not the thinks they had on top of their head when they went in. The 3 questions are meant to get starter not the end point. A lot of scrum is simplified because it’s easy to teach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some people say we already know what’s wrong and how to fix it so we don’t need a retrospective.&lt;/strong&gt; But they arrived to that conclusion alone and not with the team. And other people may disagree or not interpret the symptoms the same way, they may think the cause of the symptoms is different. And you don’t learn this unless you dig in from multiple prospectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lot of people like to use the 5 whys to go to the root cause of something. In my experience nothing has a single root cause.&lt;/strong&gt; Any behavior that persistent has a feedback loop that maintains that. People move from 5 why to a fishbone diagram that allows for multiple root causes but if you dig deeper what’s contributing to each of them? If you look you’ll find &lt;strong&gt;reinforcing or inhibiting loops&lt;/strong&gt; within the team, the organization or elsewhere. Once you can visualize it maybe you can remedy. Counteract or balance it somewhere else. &lt;strong&gt;Causal Loop Diagrams come from system thinking&lt;/strong&gt;. There is a lot of books about it out there &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Fifth-Discipline-Practice-Learning-Organization/dp/0385517254&quot;&gt;The 5th discipline&lt;/a&gt; by Peter Senge and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/714348.Quality_Software_Management&quot;&gt;Quality Software Management: Systems Thinking&lt;/a&gt; by Gerald Weinberg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One of the first facilitation skills I often see is allowing people to voice their thoughts&lt;/strong&gt;. If you’re rotating facilitator maybe you can learn from each other. You don’t need a professional retrospective facilitator. I haven’t studied facilitation. I learn from some great facilitators.  You don’t need huge confidence facilitation skills to facilitate a retrospective. If group is trying to work together they will help facilitate and step in if you overlooked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe people say we don’t need a retrospective. We see a problem we see a solution. That’s true, don’t wait for the retrospective just do it. &lt;strong&gt;During the retrospective I say we need to look at it more deeply at what actually happened&lt;/strong&gt;. Looking together is the best tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focusing the goal of a retrospective is not always so narrow it preclude someone else’s topic&lt;/strong&gt;. But if it’s really important to someone that it should be included in the goal of the retrospective. In a team if an individual has a problem the whole team has a problem. The structure of a retrospective is not so rigid, if you’re on generating insights but realize you missed something we can go back to gathering data for some specific issue before you moving again to generating insights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Retrospective for groups larger then 15 people is where your facilitation skill get more critical&lt;/strong&gt;. You might struggle to have everyone on the same page. But you can get them more on that. One of the issues I see unwillingness to stick out from the crowd. Exercises when you write first and talk later are helpful. Ensuring it’s a safe environment is also especially critical in large groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The retrospective facilitators gathering is a small open space conference&lt;/strong&gt;. Runs for a week. Pretty open in topic. People get more deep in to the topic. Everyone there is a facilitator. I personally got a lot out of it. You get a lot of different viewpoints. A great change to disconnect from the world and seeing what challenges people are facing and learn from others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s by invitation first to the people that attended the previous year and then goes to the people recommended. People can contact me if they’re interested in early May this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;favorite-retrospective-activity&quot;&gt;Favorite retrospective activity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pick activities that would help a particular group in a particular situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I have no background on the team I used to use the timeline. But now my go-to is FRIM (FRequency IMpact) by Diana Larsen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;book-reading-right-now&quot;&gt;Book reading right now&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/611437.Making_Contact&quot;&gt;Making Contact by Virginia Satir&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;favorite-dish&quot;&gt;Favorite dish&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steamed crabs with melted butter and spices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guest&quot;&gt;Guest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;George Dinwiddie helps organizations develop software more effectively. He brings decades of development experience from electronic hardware and embedded firmware to business information technology. He helps organizations, managers, and teams solve the problems they face by providing consulting, coaching, mentoring and training at the organizational, process, team, interpersonal, and technical levels. Involved in the Agile community since 2000, he has helped groups ranging from a 6-person startup to a Fortune 100 company and a billion-plus dollar federal program, either directly or in partnership with other companies. He is the author of Evolutionary Anatomy of Test Automation Code and co-author of Patterns of Agile Journeys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/gdinwiddie&quot;&gt;@gdinwiddie&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;gdinwiddie@idiacomputing.com&quot;&gt;gdinwiddie@idiacomputing.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/george_dinwiddie.png&quot; alt=&quot;George Dinwiddie&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/the-end-goal-of-a-retrospective</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/the-end-goal-of-a-retrospective</guid>
        
        
        <category>season one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Remote retrospectives challenges and advantages</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this episode we talk with David Horowitz creator of &lt;a href=&quot;http://retrium.com&quot;&gt;Retrium&lt;/a&gt; about the challenges–and advantages–of remote retrospectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/566473794%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-G6dOR&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you find it hard to run remote retrospectives? Have you perhaps given up because the team is so disengaged? In this episode we will help with that interviewing David Horowitz creator of &lt;a href=&quot;http://retrium.com&quot;&gt;Retrium&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;here-are-a-few-highlights-from-david&quot;&gt;Here are a few highlights from David:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I had to define agile in two words I’d use: continuous improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agile rests on two pillars: product improvement and process improvement. Everyone understand product improvement, but we often forget how we work together–process improvement–is equally important. A team that has  been together for 1 week or 1 month should be less efficient or productive then a team together for much longer. This assumption rest on the assumption that we learn together. The demo is the meeting that catalyzes product improvement and feedback to me the retrospective is the meeting that catalyzes the process improvement part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The goal of a retrospective is learning&lt;/strong&gt;. Focus on–hopefully–one area and learn collectively–instead of on your own–so the team can go forward in the next iteration and improve. Without a retrospective we can learn on our own–or watercooler conversation between two individuals–but if we’re trying to learn as a team we need to be together in the same room… physically or virtually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you ask an agile purist he’d probably say there is no such thing as a remote team in agile. But we live in a geographically displaced world. Most software is built in a distributed fashion. People across continents or perhaps in the same building across different floors. You probably send instant messages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In my mind if you have just one person on your team that is remote then you have a remote team.&lt;/strong&gt; Suppose you have a 10 person team, 9 sitting in a meeting room and one calling in. Imagine you’re that person calling in. Do you have an equal play field? Or to voice your ideas? Understand the conversation? Probably not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Once one person is remote we need to act as a remote team.&lt;/strong&gt; In regards to retrospectives, you have lots of colocated facilitation techniques but if you have one person remote I don’t think you can use the same techniques. Unless everyone can participate in the meeting it’s an unfair situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When a single person is remote a buddy–in the room–can be assigned&lt;/strong&gt;. The buddy’s job is not just to participate themself but to bubble up the other person’s ideas/feelings/input and make sure they keep involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other ways to encouraging more equal engagement when you have a remote team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One thing I suggest is if there is one remote make everybody remote&lt;/strong&gt;. So if one is dialing in to the meeting make everyone dial in. This might work or not but experimenting with it is a way to encourage engagement and empathy for the people that will always have to dial in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is baseline and baseline per team basis. If video is an option and people are willing to go on video that’s obviously better then voice. If people don’t have video and have voice that’s obviously better then text for most teams. But that’s something that you can discover culturally as you learn together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is always some individuals that just prefer just audio. To me this is foreign, but there are some legitimate reason for it. Some are embarrassed about their home tidiness, others have poor bandwidth/rural so can’t have video on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need a communication mechanism but what that is should be up to the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked for a large bank and we had people spread around the US and Asia and Europe. That’s where I realized how challenging remote retrospectives are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The offshore team did not have bandwidth for video so it was just audio. It was a round-robin activity to brainstorm ideas. It was naive of me to expect this activity to keep them engaged. There was complete silence from the phone. Finally I said here are 10 ideas, let’s see the complexity. And it was fascinated what happened. People in the room reflected and voted the complexity. The remote people went silent and after 5 minutes “we estimate it to be a five”. This was a poor facilitation on my side and that event made it click that there was work to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a web form to submit ideas is a good first step. If you follow the 5 steps format you need a bit more structure so I decided to quit my job and build &lt;a href=&quot;http://retrium.com&quot;&gt;Retrium.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When the team is remote you need to be more intentional about un-intentional conversations&lt;/strong&gt;. When colocated you end up having water-cooler conversations or other type of face to face conversations. When you work remotely you need to have at least a joking instant message channel–like a virtual water-cooler area. That’s not enough in my opinion. You need more then asynchronous conversation. What I suggest is to ping people when you go grab a coffee and keep a zoom chat open while you both grab coffee. And very intentionally you do not talk about work. The same applies to retrospectives too.Whatever you’d do to prep for your co-located retrospective you can do remote, you just have to be more intentional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remote facilitation is something I would not recommend to people new to facilitation&lt;/strong&gt;. People don’t realize facilitation is a skill that you need to learn and hone. Skills take time to learn. If you’re new to facilitation, start with a job that allows you to learn in a co-located environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When you facilitate remotely you have a few extra challenges: a big one is engagement&lt;/strong&gt;. I recommend to hand off your facilitation duties to one of the remote people. If you’re trying to learn collectively the person that is going to limit how much the team is gonna learn is likely to be the remote person. Try to give that person the role of the facilitator to keep them more engaged and to slow down to a pace that keeps everyone involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anyone can volunteer to be the facilitator it should not be an assigned role.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t find anyone in your team look outside, perhaps create a &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.retrium.com/circle-of-facilitators&quot;&gt;circle of retrospective facilitators&lt;/a&gt; in your company. Your toolbox is limited, but if you bring in someone from the outside they can bring a new prospective and new tools. Another advantage is they can bring in a new vantage point on the organization and they might bring more ideas about what worked for other teams in the organization. &lt;strong&gt;One downside is if the team doesn’t feel safe to speak up it’s very unlikely you’ll arrive to learning. If you bring in an external facilitator you’re pushing the limit on psychological safety.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Team should volunteer to have external facilitator or you risk people won’t speak up.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everybody talk about how hard it is to be remote–and it’s true–but there are some things that are easier. It’s harder to be fully anonymous in person then online. Prioritizing with dot voting online can be non-leading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Many people call retrospectives boring cause nothing is changing after them! It’s a natural reaction&lt;/strong&gt;. The root cause of most retros is it’s not improving your life. It’s important to focus on one area/experiment at the end of retrospective but if no-one has volunteer to be the task ambassador–to drive that change, to followup on that–the idea of collective responsibility gets superseded by day to day work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have many possible actions on the table how do you know which one to pick? Try &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.futureworksconsulting.com/blog/2008/05/16/impact-and-energy/&quot;&gt;Idea/Effort/Impact/Energy/Commitment = IEIEC&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dot vote on ideas to visualize what’s gonna have impact, take less effort and have energy behind it. When you use this approach usually someone will commit to be the &lt;strong&gt;task ambassador&lt;/strong&gt; to drive the change trough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key to understand how to engage with introverts is that they want to share their ideas in a way they’re more comfortable sharing it. As an introvert I used to hate group conversation. But I had ideas. If in meetings I was presented with stick-notes and give time to think and process before being but on the spot I would have been very happy to share my ideas. &lt;strong&gt;If you’re trying to encourage more introverted people to participate in a remote retrospective give them a communication paradigm they’re comfortable on.&lt;/strong&gt; If you put them on the step and ask them “do you have an idea?” you’ll probably get silence.  Usually a more asynchronous communication paradigm–so they have more time to think–and also more written will give you wider adoption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a set of facilitation techniques on &lt;a href=&quot;http://retrium.com&quot;&gt;Retrium&lt;/a&gt; that would have made my past remote retrospectives easier. We have activities to keep the retrospective format diverse and engaging: lean coffee, start/stop/continue, team radar. We think of it as an educational tool. Guided by the best practices in our industry. The platform will guide you trough the activities and you’ll learn as you go trough the process. &lt;strong&gt;Inexperienced retrospective facilitators have a lot to gain by adopting Retrium because it’s a learning resource in addition of a real time collaboration tool.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most team run retros and they can solve issues at team level but at some point they’ll identify an issue outside of our control. Most teams will just move on. But the issue will come up again. If it’s really preventing your productivity that’s a problem. One thing we’d like to do in Retrium–if you identify 5 action changes–you can mark 2 or 3 to share with the larger organization. That’s transparent information sharing but it’s hard to operationalize without software. If you’re a company at scale that data will get lost at some point. We want to make Retrium not just for teams but for organizational change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;favorite-activity&quot;&gt;Favorite activity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.retrium.com/the-30-second-retrospective&quot;&gt;The 30 seconds retrospective&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;book-reading-right-now&quot;&gt;Book reading right now&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Alexander-Hamilton-Ron-Chernow/dp/0143034758&quot;&gt;Alexander Hamilton&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;favorite-dish&quot;&gt;Favorite dish&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can only one thing in life it would be Churros!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guest&quot;&gt;Guest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Horowitz is the CEO &amp;amp; Co-Founder of Retrium. Prior to co-founding &lt;a href=&quot;http://retrium.com&quot;&gt;Retrium&lt;/a&gt;, he was a software developer turned agile coach at The World Bank and International Finance Corporation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/ds_horowitz&quot;&gt;@ds_horowitz&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;david@retrium.com&quot;&gt;david@retrium.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/david_horowitz.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;David Horowitz&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 02 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/remote-retrospectives-challenges-and-advantages</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/remote-retrospectives-challenges-and-advantages</guid>
        
        
        <category>season one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The five steps retrospective framework</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this episode we talk with Diana Larsen about the origins and reasons for the 5 steps framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/566409198%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-vlBz9&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diana co-authored “Agile Retrospectives - Making good teams great”. Have you ever wondered why you’d need a 5 steps framework? What’s wrong in just adding items to 3 columns and picking action items? Read on or listen to the episode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;here-are-a-few-highlights-from-diana&quot;&gt;Here are a few highlights from Diana:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in 1996 Norm couldn’t facilitate cause he was the manager of the team so he asked me to facilitate. He knew I had experience facilitating meetings around team development. That was my first retrospective. He gave me an unpublished manuscript of his book “project retrospectives”, I met Esther Derby trough norm and we got both very involved with the growing community of  what was later named agile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As we worked we realized there needed to be something other the end of project retrospectives in the agile space&lt;/strong&gt;. We talked with others in the industry like Rachel Davis and Tim McKinnon and realized we needed retrospectives around the iterative cadence of agile. A time not just for the organization to look back at how to improve projects but for the team to look Back at the how to improve how they work together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started writing about what we were doing differently then Norm, and we looked at other facilitation sources: one from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.icacan.org&quot;&gt;The institute of cultural affairs in Canada&lt;/a&gt; (the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.icacan.org/books/the-art-of-focused-conversation/&quot;&gt;Art of focused conversations&lt;/a&gt;, one from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hsdinstitute.org&quot;&gt;Human system dynamics&lt;/a&gt; (the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hsdinstitute.org/resources/adaptive-action-guide.html&quot;&gt;adaptive action&lt;/a&gt; format).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All shared first an assessment of the current situation. Then once you have clarity look in to what insights can we get–an analytical phase versus the initial descriptive phase–and then comes a decision phase. Now what do we want to do about that? Where is the best place to put our energy. &lt;strong&gt;That became gather data, generate insights, generate what to do.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also knew most of the people that pick up our book were not trained facilitators they where software folks and were not expected to have those skills. It’s interesting to see how those facilitation techniques have become more important now then they were back then. &lt;strong&gt;We realized we needed to give our audience a way to start the retrospective meeting (set the stage) and then at the end close the retrospective (to shift from this meeting to whatever work is coming after)&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we determined those 5 steps where the best combination for people we started assigning activities from our experience and from other colleagues and the total quality methods.
This is how the 5 steps came to be, so that people would have all the understanding that they needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As we were writing the book we would often get questions like: “I don’t understand how you could write a whole book about retrospectives it’s just two questions”. Having the lists don’t make you close to any action.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“You build models, you put them out in to the world and they teach you back.” I look at my coffee cup and I think,”oh it’s only half full” does it mean I want to get more coffee? Maybe I’ll wait till later. That’s gather data, generate insights, decide what to do. &lt;strong&gt;With the 5 steps we take a group of people so they can simultaneously go trough the same thinking process that an individual goes trough. That’s the real power in it. That’s why we suggest people not to leave out parts or you’d miss out on some of the thinking process.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Institute of cultural affairs has ORID Observation, Reflection, Interpretation, Decision. We collapsed observation and reflection (on how you reacted to that situation) in to gather data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Things happened but the real crux is how do we respond to the things?&lt;/strong&gt; If I go back to the coffee cup example, on some day if I knock it off I might be just go along with my days but other times I might be very hard on myself and let it ruin my whole day. It’s not just about having knocked over my coffee cup… that’s a fact… there is coffee all over my desk… what’s really important is how did I respond to that? How did that influence my subsequent behavior? And when you’re in a group, maybe I am fine having knocked it over but other people around are not. And that’s another dynamic. So being able to pull out those dynamics is an important step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generating insights is—after we make sure we’re all on the same page about what happened—can we see some patterns? Notice things that are new? Or happening again? What are the causes that make us trip? We only have our own point of view until we take this broader scan and share with the group. &lt;strong&gt;Generating insights is where the learning happens. We learn about the implications of what happened. How did it affect us?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When we wrote the book there wasn’t much information about complexity frameworks like &lt;a href=&quot;https://cognitive-edge.com&quot;&gt;David Snowden’s Cynefin&lt;/a&gt; that can help to get some sense what kinda of approach we should take based on where the problem falls: simple, complicated, complex.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tackling something that the team control first helps to build their muscles around team improvement. As the team improve and start seeing more patterns they can start looking in to influencing actions. But they need to get a clear picture of what they’re doing together first. In some ways it’s a fluency progression. The first way that you become fluent is deal with the problems that are internal to the team. Things that the team has direct control over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the agile fluency there are four cumulative zones for the teams. It’s not a maturity model. Not all organization need an optimizing team. The zones are: focusing, delivering, optimizing, strengthening. Retrospectives for the teams in the focusing zone are going to be focused on how well are they working together, is there anything they need to adjust in their work process? In the delivery zone the nature of the retrospective is going to change, questions like are we using all the engineering practice that we are creating the smallest about of bugs in our code so that our integrations can go smoothly. &lt;strong&gt;The nature of the kinda of things you’re looking in your retrospectives changes depending on what zone you’re developing fluency in&lt;/strong&gt;. In optimizing the team would retrospect more on cross functional collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rotating facilitators is a great idea&lt;/strong&gt;. In the book we said if nobody has those facilitation skills we should bring in an external facilitator. That was back then, now some of those permanent skills are more widespread. When everyone is involved in facilitation I noticed in a group of 7 maybe only 2/3 have an affinity for facilitation meeting and are interested in developing more skill. A lot of the times these are the people that rotate. The idea is you don’t need your scrum-master to do it and that people can develop facilitation skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things we noticed in the Agile community is every terms get coopted and get used in the way people want to use it. &lt;strong&gt;So people leading retrospectives hopping trough the 3 columns, trying to find an immediate action items without digging any deeper for insights… might call what they’re doing facilitating but it’s not&lt;/strong&gt;. Or they’re facilitating in a very minimal kinda… not even good enough for now level. Just going trough the motions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;True facilitation is really leading people trough steps they need can to go trough to as a group to be able to think together to be able to come to some conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Where-Action-Meetings-Break-Organization/dp/1732205205&quot;&gt;Where the action by Elise Keith&lt;/a&gt; is a book about the 16 type of meetings that go on to really understand what kinda of work are we trying to accomplish to help this group to get to the outcome they need right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We want to everyone gets good facilitation skills—in all meetings, demo, planning, standup and of course retrospective&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There is a fallacy that we think that because we’re human we’re born with the skill of listening to each other, the skill at communication what we mean, and having a meeting together and it’s just not true&lt;/strong&gt;. Just like reading and writing and math and computer programming these are skills you need to develop over time to become effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We should focus our retrospectives on a topic because a lot of things happen during an iteration&lt;/strong&gt;. Influenced by a lot of things. We’re not given enough time to dig deeper, someone has to make the judgment call, what are the things that stand out in this iteration? Where does it stand in the complexity spectrum? Is it a complex situation? Obvious? How is our decision making around this. If we look at the lists and spend a couple of minutes and try to come to a conclusion we haven’t really given the depth of analysis to what gives rise to each of those either enablers or constraints things that got in our way. We don’t have enough time to really examine those so we can get away from the whack-a-mole so we can really deal with what has generated those conditions to occur. Until we look in depth we can’t really know how to improve the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may have things in your team that you need to deal across a number of iterations… a number of retrospectives. Re-opening up the whole list just confuses the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How much time for a retrospective depends on the size of the group&lt;/strong&gt;. Bigger group requires longer time. For a group to 4-6 people, in my experience most groups would take just about 75 minutes. Teams that know how to think together can conclude in less then 1 hour. I would play around with the length of time. There is almost no people that can come to substantial improvement action in half an hour. All you’ll do is go back to the 3 columns list and that’s not gonna move you forward. That’s why I think it’s a waste of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;favourite-activity&quot;&gt;Favourite activity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Circle of questions (only work in groups of 8/10)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;book-reading-right-now&quot;&gt;Book reading right now&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessmodelsforteams.com&quot;&gt;Business models for teams by Tim Clark and Bruce Hazen&lt;/a&gt;, looking for connection with agile fluency&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;favorite-dish&quot;&gt;Favorite dish&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Vietnamese dish called Bun&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guest&quot;&gt;Guest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A visionary pragmatist, Diana Larsen is co-founder and Chief Connector at the Agile Fluency™ Project, where we hold a vision of an inspiring future: “Every agile software team practices Agile Software Development at a level of fluent proficiency that specifically fits their businesses’ needs.”. Diana co-authored books Agile Retrospectives: Making Good Teams Great;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DianaOfPortland&quot;&gt;@DianaOfPortland&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.futureworksconsulting.com/about/diana-larsen&quot;&gt;https://www.futureworksconsulting.com/about/diana-larsen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/diana_larsen.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Diana Larsen&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/the-five-steps-retrospective-framework</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/the-five-steps-retrospective-framework</guid>
        
        
        <category>season one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Introduce change in retrospectives</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this episode we talk with Linda Rising about introducing changes to our retrospective facilitation and how the latest neuroscience research can help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/563782692%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-09Kql&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;here-are-a-few-highlights-from-linda&quot;&gt;Here are a few highlights from Linda:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I wrote software for the Boeing 777 I was brought in to transition from Pascal to Ada but found a lot of resistors. They started writing Adatran because they were never convinced about the switch. You can’t bring a new language and just change how people think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We need to realise we’re all biased, and it’s impossible to look at the world from another person’s point of view. Instead we can make sure the group has diversity. Somebody that has a different point of view… a skeptic is someone that disagree with us and asks good questions. If we all agree we’re probably all sharing the same bias.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On changing retrospective format:&lt;/em&gt; You can’t change other people. You can listen to them and ask why they do what they do. Ask them to tell you. In that explanation things will come out. You can phrase it as an experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The message of Agile is that we’re learning. We do the best we can with what we know right now. Realizing how inadequate it is but it will move us forward.&lt;/strong&gt; The US is facing a political division the solution is hard but you can take baby steps and move forward. An example is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.better-angels.org&quot;&gt;Better angels&lt;/a&gt; an organization to de-polarize the US by listening to each other. You can always begin. That is a hopeful approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are a collection of patterns from Fearless change that are essential no-matter what you’re trying to change:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you have to care about it (Evangelist pattern)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;little tiny iterations (Just do it pattern)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how did that work (reflection pattern)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;build on that (small successes pattern)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;move forward (baby steps pattern)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;we later found out that’s call the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.simplypsychology.org/learning-kolb.html&quot;&gt;Kolb learning cycle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Legacy system was gonna die the company wanted the new project to succeeded costed lots of money and produced nothing. What is we can do to learn something from this? How to make sure it doesn’t happen again? Norm Kerth was writing his book on Project retrospectives so he help me, he was generous and shared his wisdom and ideas on how do you learn from success and failures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I was learning I started going to the Retrospective Facilitator Gathering and learn–implicit knowledge instead of explicit learning–more about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the very first retrospective the primary thing I avoided talking about the project failure. It would have been valuable for them to talk about it but that’s what I knew then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without retrospectives a company would have big knowledge holes about what happens. When you’re introducing retrospectives for the first time I would not advertise that I don’t know very much. If you’re too forthcoming and honest and say you don’t know that much other people will think “oh you don’t know what you’re doing” and you won’t have credibility. Don’t lie about what you know but don’t bring it out because we all start that way. Just do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a pattern “pick your battles” to realize that sometimes it’s not the right time. Maybe people were not ready for it, or you or the company. If it’s not going well just wait and then you should try again. Because the context–people, you, the company–keeps changing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a fan of continuous retrospective. Don’t wait for the retrospective to remember what happened instead people can add items to a timeline as events happen. Adding the items and letting system 2–your subconscious–kick in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;System 1 and system 2 is from “Thinking fast and thinking slow”. A behavioral model for how the brain operates. System 1–the unconscious–is System 2–the conscious. System 1 is fast system 2 is slow. System 1 can remember a lot, system 2 is very forgetful. System 2 is the limited logical part of our brain. System 1 can work while we sleep… it’s a background process. Don’t waste time trying to come up with things, hand it over to system 1. System 1 is biased and it needs a sensor or a driver that’s system 2. Neuroscience fits better with a continuous retrospectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t use system 1 on command you can’t force it or you can’t predict. But you also can’t just sit in a room to wait for a great idea to come up via system 2. You can do it now and produce something that is not very good or wait until tomorrow and have a great idea. Sometime I hear “we’re not leaving this room until the discussion is done”, there is evidence that taking a break before the decision is made there are better outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5 whys is such a waste of time. System 2 can make up a reason and it has no clue, system 1 knows much more but there is no way you can just inquire it in real time. What you get is system 2 rationalization. You don’t get any closer to the truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s the exciting thing about cognitive neuroscience. What we know now compared to what we knew 2 years ago is definitely changing and has impacts on what we do. I don’t force anything. If I need to give a talk at a conference or at a company I collect the context and then leave it. Hours later something happens. I know what I should do and put it together. Instead of forcing it, sit down and get it done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;favorite-retrospective-activity&quot;&gt;Favorite retrospective activity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Offer appreciations. I have dozens of stories. It can be implemented in many different ways. But everyone was a hero in the last iteration. Sit there until we’re all done, at the end people that were unhappy, unsure if they wanted to be on the team or not will feel different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;book-i-am-reading&quot;&gt;Book I am reading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Gut-Feelings-Intelligence-Gerd-Gigerenzer/dp/0143113763&quot;&gt;Gut feelings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;favourite-dish&quot;&gt;Favourite dish&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have one… but since this was recorded around Christmas, it’s a nutbread my mum used to make and reminds me of her. &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/Ruths_Fruitcake.docx&quot;&gt;Download the recipe of Linda’s fruitcake&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guest&quot;&gt;Guest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linda Rising is an independent consultant who lives near Nashville, Tennessee. Linda has a Ph.D. from Arizona State University in object-based design metrics. Her background includes university teaching as well as work in industry in telecommunications, avionics, and tactical weapons systems. She is an internationally known presenter on topics related to agile development, patterns, retrospectives, the change process, and the connection between the latest neuroscience and software development. Linda is the author of numerous articles and five books. The latest, More Fearless Change, co-authored with Mary Lynn Manns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/risinglinda&quot;&gt;@risinglinda&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://lindarising.org&quot;&gt;http://lindarising.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/linda_rising.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Linda Rising&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/introduce-change</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/introduce-change</guid>
        
        
        <category>season one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Becoming a facilitator</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this episode we talk with Ryan Latta about his journey becoming a retrospective facilitator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/585584835%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-l8kHp&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ryan shares some challenges he faced of running retrospectives and when he discovered facilitating retrospectives is more then adding items to three columns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;here-are-a-few-highlights-from-ryan&quot;&gt;Here are a few highlights from Ryan:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Before my scrum master went to retrospective facilitation training we always had a retrospective with 3 columns&lt;/strong&gt;–what went well, what didn’t go so well, what we want to change–dot vote and create action item. After the training I saw a more effective format and activity that digged topics deeper then the 3 columns. That’s when I realized there is a lot more to retrospective then what I first tought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Action items look similar but the journey that got to produce the action item has so much meaning to the team that the team doesn’t really need to know the action item exists. I don’t need to put it on a wall or in a backlog it just naturally happens and gets done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every single retrospective the team came up with action items. Before they tought this was a time set aside to complain but now are so much better they said. Why I asked? They listed all the action items for the last 7 retrospectives (5 months). What is that happens I asked? They created a set of rules for how to run a retrospective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hinge points of a retrospective is generating insights. That’s the part where teams create meaning. Far too much of a hurry in getting to an action item. Be intentional about creating time for the team to create meaning about what they do. One action item is better then 3 that nobody will do. I have the group go trough divergent opinions–casting the net very wide–then the act of converging is distilling all that down to the ones we want to invest in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In my retrospectives I don’t ask for perfect and definitive instead I ask for likely and plausible.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ask to prioritize to get to a focus for the retrospective. I often ask debriefing questions: “what about this was challenging?”, “what did we miss?” leading in to the final question “what’s the meaning of all this?” and see what they say. If the group agree that’s the insight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This group I worked with was not working well togheter–I understood there were emotions involved–when we went trough mad/sad/glad but there were F-Bombs dropped people crying. I asked them if everyone was working with good intentions, and the best job they could. So I asked if all this hurt wasn’t because we wanted to hurst one another but rather because things didn’t go well. People agreed. I asked if that’s ok to apologies for the hurt. The group did and after that things started getting better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Given what I know now I would have paid more attention to what is about to walk in that room talk more to these people before the retrospective&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I prepare for a retrospective because the group deserves that. I spend up to 1 hour to prepare a retrospective that is right for them at that time. I plan not to control it but to be prepared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retrospectives must be a safe space. When a facilitator hold power over the team–ie. a manager or a product owner–I reccomand to reflect on hot to begin the retrospective. For example look at &lt;a href=&quot;http://retrospectivewiki.org/index.php?title=The_Prime_Directive&quot;&gt;Kerth’s prime directive&lt;/a&gt; burn it in to their heart and then do a safety check.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When a room is full of individual that feel unsafe I run all the activities anonymously and dig in to what do you think has to change for the safety to change&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t care who facilitates. I think rotating facilitator is often because facilitation is not acknowledged as a skill. If people want to learn facilitation skills it’s fine to have them rotate in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team has to give permissions for managers and stakeholders to be present during team retrospective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;whats-your-favourite-retrospective-activity&quot;&gt;What’s your favourite retrospective activity?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mad, sad glad&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Jean Tabaka’s sailboat&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mindmap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;whats-a-book-your-reading-now&quot;&gt;What’s a book your reading now?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Habits-Highly-Effective-People-Powerful/dp/0743269519&quot;&gt;7 habits of higly effective people&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;thinking fast and thinking slow review&quot;&gt;Thinking fast and thinking slow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Martian-Andy-Weir/dp/0553418025&quot;&gt;The martian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;whats-your-favourite-dish&quot;&gt;What’s your favourite dish?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tacos with veggies. A really well made steak. Pizza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guest&quot;&gt;Guest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ryan Latta has been building software and teams for nearly 10 years now. He currently works as an agile coach and scrum master with a mission of creating teams that change the world. He has had the pleasure of working in a number of industries including: banking, video game, education, advertising, and automotive. When he isn’t spending time with his family, he is mentoring new developers in starting their careers, playing games, and learning to play the fiddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/recursivefaults&quot;&gt;@recursivefaults&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ryanlatta.com&quot;&gt;http://www.ryanlatta.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/ryan_latta.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ryan Latta&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2019 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/becoming-a-retrospective-facilitator</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/becoming-a-retrospective-facilitator</guid>
        
        
        <category>season one</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What is a powerful retrospective</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In this first episode we talk with Esther Derby about what a retrospective really is and the role of the facilitator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/575725029%3Fsecret_token%3Ds-KXZeI&amp;amp;color=%23ff5500&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered what a retrospective really is? What’s the role of the facilitator? Is it just to pick an activity… time box discussions, move on to the next item… write down the action items and assign it to someone? Well if only retrospective facilitation was that simple… what are things to watch out for? What are things to strive for? In this initial episode we invited Esther Derby to answer some of these questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;here-are-a-few-highlights-from-esther&quot;&gt;Here are a few highlights from Esther:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started my career as a programmer, and I wore many hats since then: team lead, testing, dev-manager. Facilitation served me well in all these roles. I started doing Weinberg style technical reviews where a lot of attention was dedicated to ensure it was safe to talk about the code without criticizing the person that wrote the code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A retrospective is a special meeting for the team to learn and find agency so that they can take risks on their own behalf and make their worklife better&lt;/strong&gt;. Often people outside the Information Technology and agile space think about art retrospectives where you look at an artist’s body of work or past body of work. That’s what we do when we look at a team work–so people can understand patterns and how their action affect outcomes and how collaborate so they can make changes and better product. It’s about continuous improvement with agency rests in the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The role of the retrospective facilitator is to create an environment and a process so the team can have the discussion they need to have. Not all retrospective require a facilitator but all retrospectives do require some facilitation–oftentime by someone in the group that has those skills: thinking about a process to help learn and decide together, understanding the underpinning of the 5 steps retrospective:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set focus / stage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diverge to expand the pool of knowledge (Gather data)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Converge (Generate insights)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decide what to do&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Close&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Often groups converge prematurely producing habitual or not very deep thinking… just comfortable thinking that do not get to the real problem. This is an issue particularly in cultures that value deciciveness and speed. Part of the facilitation is to slow the group so they can diverge and develop insights and make decisions.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the signs a retrospective is not working are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there is no outcome or there is an “outcome” that nobody believe in&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if there is very little participation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if they are always talking about the same thing–that might be a problem with the facilitation or with a pressured environment that doesn’t give enough time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Without a retrospective a team might not be able to develop a sense of agency&lt;/strong&gt;. A sense of agency is a term that come from psicology and means “I can act on my own behalf”. I see a lot of workplaces where people are tought to be passive and need to ask for permission for so many things that they assume they have to ask for permissions for everything. When teams believe only the system–i.e. a commitee–drives the behaviour that can lead to passivity like “oh we can’t change it, it’s the system” but there are always things we can change to impact the environment and make it more conducive to the work you do. &lt;strong&gt;If nothing else you can always change your response.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked with a group that couldn’t change the process that was mandated–and only changed–by a certain group. So they changed how they responded to that when something wasn’t working. So the group developed a way to influence the committee that could change things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another group the VP would barge in and create more stories in the middle of the sprint. The group could not lock the VP out so they changed how they responded to that and developed a little script. When the VP would come in with more stories everyone would repeat the same sentence: “we understand that’s important to you, what should we take off the sprint in order to accomplish that?”. They would just repeat that. Eventually that changed his behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An activity to identify what’s in our control is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.innovationgames.com/circles-and-soup/&quot;&gt;Circles and soup&lt;/a&gt;, what we can influence and what’s in the soup. &lt;strong&gt;One of the things we can always control is our response&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use the 5 steps format for 90% of the retrospective I work on because it mirrors a tought process: focus, diverge, converge. It takes advantage of how people think when they think clearly. I’ve been in organizations when retrospectives started as a list of opinions (what did we do well, what shall we do differently), dot voting. That’s not a bad part of a retro but it’s not sufficient. I start where they are and slow things down. I usually ask if there is a focus for this particular week instead of just a laundry list. If they’re deciding what to focus on during the retrospective there is little opportunity to gather objective data. Deciding what to talk about and being hampered cause there is no more time. Objective and subjective data are equally important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t object to occasionally use retrospective to chill as long as this is not happening is all retrospectives and as long as it’s not a place where people prepare their grocery lists for weekend shopping. That tells me people aren’t finding anything useful in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having an agenda ahead of time and the topic helps people. If I am concerned about safety I’ll spend more time on tackling that and then gently introduce the new format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Developers can facilitate their team retrospectives&lt;/strong&gt;. If you’re part of the team and also the facilitator you need to make real clear which hat you’re wearing. I am reluctant in having managers facilitating retrospectives unless it’s a completely safe environment. Having some facilitation training is really important, I like the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ica-international.org/icas-technology-of-participation-top/&quot;&gt;technology of participation&lt;/a&gt; methods that came out of the work of the ICA (Institute for Cultural Affairs) so they tested these facilitation around the world. I prefer that to training that focus on specific tecquiques.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can fit the 5 steps in 15 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;set the stage&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;gather data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;generate insights&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;decide what to do&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;close out (a retrospective on the retrospective)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The retro on retrospective only takes a few minutes and it’s a signal that anything can be reflected on including the retrospective.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on the situation I might put more time on one step rather then another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some traits important to retrospective facilitation are: staying out of the content, patience–people think at different speeds, empathy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A team that’s been doing retrospectives and is familiar with agency they may come up with a focus during the retrospective. I find with teams that are not accustomed to work this way it helps to have an agile coach choose a focus before the retrospective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;favourite-retrospective-activity&quot;&gt;Favourite retrospective activity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have one. The favourite is the one that works with the team I am working with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;book-i-am-reading&quot;&gt;Book I am reading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Michelle Obama’s biography&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accounting for Slavery&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The Norman Invasion of England&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;favourite-dish&quot;&gt;Favourite dish&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Varies by season and by year, braised beef with wine and lot of polenta and pecorino.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guest&quot;&gt;Guest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Esther Derby is co-author of Agile Retrospectives: Making Good Teams Great, an expert in organizational dynamics, she teaches workshops and speak to groups and conferences all over the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://twitter.com/estherderby&quot;&gt;@estherderby&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.estherderby.com&quot;&gt;http://www.estherderby.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;200px&quot; src=&quot;/assets/esther_derby.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Esther Derby&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2019 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/what-is-a-powerful-retrospective</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://thisisretrospectivefacilitation.com/episodes/what-is-a-powerful-retrospective</guid>
        
        
        <category>season one</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
